<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The serasquier bassa an historical novel of the times, containing all that pass'd at the siege of Buda / out of French.</title>
            <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3208A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R235346</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11081449</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11081449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55663)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1428:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The serasquier bassa an historical novel of the times, containing all that pass'd at the siege of Buda / out of French.</title>
                  <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 136 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Rhodes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1685?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Jean de Prećhac.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699 --  Fiction.</term>
               <term>Buda (Hungary) --  History --  Siege, 1684 --  Fiction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46338:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>SERASQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IER BASSA:</hi> AN Hiſtorical NOVEL OF THE TIMES.</p>
            <p>Containing all that paſs'd AT THE SIEGE of <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of <hi>FRENCH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Rhodes,</hi> next Door to the <hi>Swan Tavern,</hi> near <hi>Brides-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:46338:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46338:2"/>
            <head>TO MADAM THE <hi>DA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PHINESS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſent you a Book, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of a Mixture of real Facts and gallant Intrigues. It bears the Name of the <hi>Seraſquier:</hi> In the mean time, this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb facs="tcp:46338:3"/>is only the Hero of the Romance, My Lord Elector of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia</hi> being the real Hero. The Glory he has acquir'd at the raiſing the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the great Actions he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Buda,</hi> in the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Sallies he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, and the ſeveral Combats, in which he repell'd the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> ſhew that he is ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated with the Blood
<pb facs="tcp:46338:3"/>of the famous Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> one of your Anceſtors, who ſo often made the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Empire trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I believed, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, you would be well pleas'd to read in repoſe the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of ſo worthy a Brother's glorious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which have given you ſo many Alarms; and this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reaſon oblig'd me to this Work, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:46338:4"/>you, that I am, with a moſt profound Reſpect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Humble and moſt Obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46338:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HAVING given you <hi>The Grand Viſier,</hi> and <hi>The Illuſtrious Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noueſe,</hi> Two <hi>Novels,</hi> mixt with <hi>Incidents</hi> of the <hi>Times,</hi> which have been favorably receiv'd by every one, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with <hi>The Seraſquier Baſſa</hi> of the ſame Author, hoping you will be no leſs ſatisfied with it, than you were with his two firſt Works. This laſt contains nothing but what is grounded on faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:46338:5"/>Memoirs, in reſpect of <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Fortune, and his Elevation to the Office of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier.</hi> As to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> you will find them here ſuch, as the exacteſt Relations have Publiſht them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46338:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>SERASQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IER BASSA:</hi> An Hiſtorical Novel OF THE TIMES.</head>
            <p>IT has ever been a Maxim with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperors to Educate in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> a great Number of Young Perſons, without any Diſtinction of Birth or Country. The Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, they receive, is ſo confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46338:6"/>to the Intereſts of the State; that all theſe Young Men, acknowledging no Kindred, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to themſelves no other aim, but the Empire's Grandeur, and the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Glory. At their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> they are uſually put into the Troops with very ſmall Pay, having neither Goods, Protection, nor any other Refuge, but the Hopes of Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Rewards by their Service. Thoſe, that want Wit and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to raiſe themſelves, paſs their Lives in a Condition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy enough; whereas thoſe, who have Merit, attain ſometimes to the greateſt Dignities of the State. It is certain, that the moſt conſiderable Officers of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, have had this Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; which is the Cauſe, that the <hi>Turks,</hi> who are in the firſt Stations, are ordinarily Men of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46338:6"/>Active Spirits, and full of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, although for the moſt part of an inſatiable Avarice, which obſcures all their good Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who is at this day ſo well known in <hi>Hungary</hi> by the Name of the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> was Educated in this Manner. He was Handſom, very Generous, and full of high Thoughts; but ſo Proud, that being yet in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> he diſdained the greateſt part of his Commarades, which much contributed to the getting him Enemies. It very often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that theſe Young Men, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain of their future Lot, joyn themſelves five or ſix together, making a kind of Union or So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, whereby they reciprocally engage themſelves to a mutual Participation, of Eſtates and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, if they have one day the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46338:7"/>Happineſs of being advanced: which promiſe is afterward per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with very much fidelity. <hi>Zouglan</hi> would never enter into any ſuch Engagements with any one. <hi>Ibrahim</hi> was the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Comarades, whom he eſteemed, and familiarly convers'd with. He lived in ſo great a Confidence of his Fortune, that he many times promiſed <hi>Ibrahim</hi> to contribute to his Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without troubling himſelf to require from him the ſame Condition. In fine <hi>Zouglan,</hi> at his going forth from the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> went to ſerve at Sea, where he gave Proofs of his Courage on many Occaſions, meriting the Applauſe of his Generals; but foreſeeing, he could at moſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to be only Bey, or Captain of a Galley, becauſe the great employs of the Sea were given
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46338:7"/>only to very experienc'd Officers, ſo limited a Charge not being ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to ſatisfie his Ambition, he reſolved to ſerve on Land, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf in the Army, the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> had on foot againſt <hi>Poland.</hi> He was not long there, e're he acquir'd a great deal of Glory. His Name became Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, and they ſpake of him in all the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Places, as of an Adventurer, that knew no dangers.</p>
            <p>Theſe happy Succeſſes aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented his natural Haughtineſs and alſo gave a jealouſie to many Officers of the Army. <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> who commanded the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry,</hi> hindring one day his going forth of the Camp with an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Horſe, he had choſen for a very bold Attempt; <hi>Zouglan</hi> ſhewed himſelf not a little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented at it, ſaying publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46338:8"/>That he would complain to the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> of <hi>Cabſtan Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi>'s having made him loſe a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorable Occaſion to deſtroy the Enemies of the <hi>Port. Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> informed of it, ſent to ſeek him in his Tent, and after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpoken to him in very out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageous Terms, threatned to treat him very ſeverely, if he ever happened to fail of the Reſpect he ow'd him. The fierce <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> penetrated with Spight, and Choler, laid his Hand on his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre. The <hi>Baſſa</hi> would have kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him on the Place, had he not been ſtayed by ſome other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, that were near him. <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> was Arreſted, and the whole Army blam'd his Action. The <hi>Baſſa</hi> would not however have it brought before the Council of War, being contented with ſending him Priſoner to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46338:8"/>of <hi>Temiſoüar,</hi> of which <hi>Selim Aga</hi> was at that time Governor. He was a Man of Service, who had acquir'd a great Eſtate by the Favor of the <hi>Sultaneſs Valida,</hi> his Protectreſs. He had a great Authority in his Government, living more like a <hi>Baſſa,</hi> than a particular Governor. He had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one fair Daughter, whom he lov'd with extream Tenderneſs: She being born in <hi>Hungary,</hi> he bred her up after the manner of the Country, making her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways eat with him, and not Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting her to the particular, and retir'd Life of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Women.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zouglan</hi> being arriv'd at the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Temiſoüar, Selim,</hi> who knew his Reputation, treated him with a great deal of Reſpect, and ſeeking to ſweeten the Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, the loſs of his Liberty
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46338:9"/>might have cauſed in him, gave him a Chamber, commodious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the Caſtle, where he was ſo ſtrictly Guarded, that none was permitted to ſee him. <hi>Selim</hi> truſted no body with him but himſelf, ſcarce ſuffering his <hi>Keaia</hi> or Intendent, tho' he were a Man, in whom he confided, to enter with him into his Priſoners Chamber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zaratima</hi> (this is the Name of <hi>Selim</hi>'s Daughter) having often heard her Father ſpeak of <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi>'s Courage, and the Gallant Actions he had done, was touch'd with his Diſgrace, through a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent, natural to Perſons of her Sex, who always bemoan the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Unfortunate. His Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not being far from her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, this gave her an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Curioſity to ſee him: which the great Precautions, her Father
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46338:9"/>us'd in Guarding him, hindred her many days from ſatisfying: But ſeeing in fine, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a little of this firſt Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, truſting his <hi>Keaia</hi> with the Care of his Priſoner, ſhe Addreſt her ſelf to this <hi>Keaia,</hi> inſtantly deſiring him to put her in ſome place, where ſhe might ſee <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> without beeing ſeen by him. The <hi>Keaia,</hi> who had a great deal of Reſpect and Complacency for his Maſters Daughter, and who foreſaw not any Inconvenience in giving her this Satisfaction, promis'd her to do what ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired, and diſpos'd a Corner in <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Antichamber, where he ſo plac'd <hi>Zaratima,</hi> that it was eaſie for her to ſee him, and attentively examine him, without the Priſoners having the leſt Knowledge of it: She found him very Handſome, the Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46338:10"/>that appeared upon his Face, having been ſo far from any way diminiſhing his good Meen, that it gave him an Air of Fierceneſs, which was not diſpleaſing to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratima.</hi> This view augmented the Compaſſion ſhe already had for his Misfortune; and perhaps ſhe was not far from paſſing to other Sentiments, when ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected, That it was not fit for a Perſon of her Birth, whom her Father deſtin'd to ſo great Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhments, to concern her ſelf ſo much with the Affairs of an Adventurer. She was aſham'd of her Curioſity, and rejected even all her Compaſſion had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto inſpir'd her with, in Favor of this unhapyy one,</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Friends labor'd ſoeffectually with <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Baſſa,</hi> that he promis'd them in fine to ſhow him Favor,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46338:10"/>on Condition he would ask him pardon in the Head of his Troops. <hi>Selim Aga</hi> took a pleaſure in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting his Priſoner with this good News, exaggerating to him the Indulgence of <hi>Cabſtan,</hi> who would not let this Affair come before the Council of War; but he was very much ſurpriz'd at the haughty Anſwer of <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who declared to him, <hi>That he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther die, than do ſo mean an Action in the preſence of the Army. Selim</hi> repreſented to him, That he ought to take the Benefit of the <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s good Will, and ſubmit to the Counſels of his Friends. His Remonſtrances were to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>Zouglan,</hi> perſiſting in his firſt Sentiments, anſwered, That he had not deſired to live, but for the acquiring of Glory, and that he ſhould think himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to bear the Name of a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46338:11"/>Souldier, ſhould he ranſom his Life, with the loſs of his Honor. Aſſoon as <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Reſolution he made his Complaint to the Council of War, and ſoon after a <hi>Cadi</hi> was ſent to <hi>Temiſoüar,</hi> to interrogate the Priſoner; which made every one judge, he would be condemn'd to loſe his Head. <hi>Selim</hi> ſpake of it to his Officers with ſorrow, not being able to forbear giving Encomiums to the Greatneſs of <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zaratima</hi> hearing them dayly Diſcourſe of <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Affairs, that he could not eſcape loſing his Life, had her firſt Sentiments awak'd by this ſorrowful News, and it was impoſſible for her, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Reſolution ſhe had made, to reſiſt the Motions of Compaſſion, inſpir'd to her by the ſad Deſtiny of a Man, of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46338:11"/>whom there were ſuch great Hopes, and who appear'd wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a better Fortune. At firſt ſhe had a thought of giving him Means to eſcape by ſeizing with Addreſs on the Keys of his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but her natural Haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the great diſtance, ſhe faw between her Fortune, and the unhappy Condition of the Priſoner, made her reject this thought. She apprehended alſo, that <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who was already very preſumptuous, might give another Interpretation to her Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, and dare to impute to more tender Sentiments, what was purely an Effect of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. Theſe Reflections made her waver along time; but in fine vanquiſh'd by the recital, ſhe heard of <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Noble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and touch'd with the Pleaſure a Gallant Mind finds
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46338:12"/>in doing a Generous Action, ſhe determin'd to procure him his Liberty, and took ſuch fit Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that ſhe entred into his Chamber, without being percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by any one, telling him, that, To ſave the Life of a Man of his Merit, ſhe had been willing to do an Action, unſuitable to her Sex. <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who expected only an Executioner to Strangle him, was ſo agreeably ſurpriz'd, both with the obliging Diſcourſe, and charming Beauty of <hi>Zarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> That he believed her at firſt to be one of thoſe Angels, who watch over the Conſecration of Men, and of whom <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſpeaks in his <hi>Alcoran;</hi> but <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima</hi> preſſing him to be gone, and not to loſe his Time in uſeleſs Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, he told her, he would have an Eternal Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo particular a Favor,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46338:12"/>and that he would make Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Life, ſhe gave him, only to employ it in her Service. <hi>Zaratima</hi> interrupted him, telling him, that ſhe quitted him of his Acknowledgement, and giving him withal to underſtand, that ſhe was <hi>Selim</hi>'s Daughter, that ſhe had no leſs Courage than he, and that ſhe knew how to make uſe of it for ſupporting, as ſhe ought, the Glory of her Birth, if ſhe ſaw him pretend to any Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for the future, from what ſhe had now done to ſave him: She would not ſo much as hear his Anſwer, but retired, after ſhe had inform'd him, what he muſt neceſſarily do to ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zouglan,</hi> being in Confuſion at the Obligations, he had to <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratima,</hi> and having his Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fill'd with her extraordinary
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46338:13"/>Beauty, repair'd to <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> where he found his old Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marade, <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> in favor with the <hi>Sultan,</hi> and poſſeſt of one of the chiefeſt Offices of the Court. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahim,</hi> who had heard of <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi>'s Gallant Actions, expreſt a great deal of Joy to ſee him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him with all the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of a ſincere Amity. <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> inform'd him of his Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the manner of his Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance. <hi>Ibrahim</hi> made him hope, he would employ the Credit of his Friends to ſtifle this Affair, procuring him in the mean time a conſiderable employ in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> ſent againſt the <hi>Morlaques,</hi> who had refus'd to pay him the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Tribute, and alſo made In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodes into the Lands of the <hi>Turks. Zouglan,</hi> finding no real Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but in ſeeking how to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46338:13"/>his Acknowledgement to the fair Perſon, that had ſav'd his Life, had at firſt, no ſmall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance to accept an employ, which removed him from <hi>Temi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoüar:</hi> Nevertheleſs, ſince he could not return into <hi>Hungary,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expoſing himſelf to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> who was very powerful, he reſolv'd to paſs into <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> where he did ſuch extraordinary Actions; that the Souldiers, wondring at the happy Succeſs of his Valor, call'd him nothing but <hi>Cheitan,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Devil.</hi> He, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded theſe Forces, being kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in an Ambuſh, which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels laid for him. <hi>Zouglan Chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> by the Credit of his Friend, or favor'd by his own Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had order to command in Chief, and to finiſh this War withal the ſpeed he could, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46338:14"/>the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> had elſewhere occaſion for his Troops. He accompliſh'd this with ſo much Courage, and Conduct, that he re-eſtabliſh'd the revolted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince in its firſt Tranquillity, and brought to the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> who was then at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> the Heads of thoſe, who had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd all this Diſorder.</p>
            <p>Theſe happy Succeſſes gain'd <hi>Zouglan</hi> a great Reputation, in which his Friend <hi>Ibrahim</hi> took as much Pleaſure, as if himſelf had vanquiſh'd the Rebels. <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> alone was inſenſible of the Applauſe, that was given him on all ſides, living perpetually in great Inquietude. He repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to himſelf every Moment his Obligation to <hi>Selim</hi>'s Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Remembrance of her Beauty augmented the Ardor and Impatience, he had to give
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46338:14"/>her Marks of his Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He met about that time an Officer of the Army in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> who told him, that <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> unmeaſurably incens'd at his Eſcape, had turn'd all his Reſentment againſt <hi>Selim Aga,</hi> whom he had got condemn'd to pay him a great Summ of Money, or to reſtore him his Priſoner; that he alſo had the Credit to diſpoſeſs him of his Government, till he had ſatisfied him. <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> was ſenſibly afflicted at the Infelicities, he had drawn upon <hi>Selim;</hi> which obliged him to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf more exactly of the particulars of this Affair. All, that the Officer had told him, was confirm'd to him, and he learn'd farther, That <hi>Selim Aga</hi> had been a long time at the <hi>Port,</hi> ſolliciting his re-eſtabliſhment, without being able to effect it;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46338:15"/>That he had brought his Daughter to the <hi>Sultaneſs Valida,</hi> at whoſe Feet he had caſt himſelf, deſiring her Protection; and that this <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs,</hi> charm'd with the Beauty of <hi>Zaratima,</hi> would have her Father leave her with her, till his Affairs were finiſh'd. The Generous <hi>Zouglan,</hi> being incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolable for his having made <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim</hi> loſe the Government of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſoüar,</hi> ſought him haſtily out, and delay'd not to put himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into his Hands, and make himſelf once more his Priſoner. <hi>Selim,</hi> tho' very much aſtoniſh'd at ſo extraordinary and bold an Action, fail'd not to make Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of it, and to demand Reparation for all the Calumnies, <hi>Cabſtan</hi> had advanced againſt him. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who, being with the <hi>Sultaneſs Valida,</hi> had confuſedly learn'd, that <hi>Selim</hi>'s Affairs were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46338:15"/>in the moſt favorable Diſpoſition, he could deſire, had at firſt an extream Joy to know, that her Father was in Condition to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Innocency; but when ſhe was inform'd of the Generous Proceeding of <hi>Zouglan,</hi> ſhe had a ſecret Inquietude for him, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming within her Soul his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great Generoſity in an Occaſion, where he hazarded no leſs than his Life. <hi>Ibrahim</hi> having acquainted the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> with this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, and with the great Actions, <hi>Zouglan</hi> had done againſt the <hi>Polanders,</hi> and the Rebellious <hi>Morlaques,</hi> the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred to have heard him ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of with Eſteem, caus'd him to be ſet at Liberty, and having forbidden any farther mention of <hi>Cabſtan</hi>'s Affair, order'd <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim</hi> to be re-eſtabliſhld in the Government of <hi>Temiſoüar.</hi> But
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46338:16"/>the <hi>Sultaneſs Valida,</hi> who was much pleas'd with <hi>Zaratima,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that her Father retir'd in the depth of Winter, would not conſent, ſhe ſhould return into <hi>Hungary;</hi> but promiſed <hi>Selim</hi> to ſend her back to him in a Seaſon, leſs incommodious for the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of long Voyages. <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Affair made a great deal of noiſe at the <hi>Port,</hi> which fail'd not to be very Glorious to him, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioning every one to learn the Particulars of his worthy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sultaneſs Valida,</hi> who was full of Wit and Addreſs, had ſtill kept a great ſhare in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. As her Authority was very great, ſo ſhe wholly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed it in procuring all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Advantages to her ſecond Son <hi>Soliman,</hi> for whom ſhe had an incredible Tenderneſs. She
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46338:16"/>had caus'd him to be educated with extraordinary Care, and had often ſtood in need of all her Skill, to avoid this Prince's giving Jealouſie to the Emperor <hi>Mahomet,</hi> his Brother, who would on many Occaſions have Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to his own ſecurity, and particularly when <hi>Sultan Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> his Son was born; but the <hi>Sultaneſs Valida</hi> had always the Dexterity to hinder it, and knew ſo well to manage the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Spirit, that he determin'd in fine, through his Mothers Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to ſettle a Revenue upon <hi>Soliman,</hi> and conſented alſo, that he ſhould retire to <hi>Burſa,</hi> which is a ſtrong Place; that was given him with all its Dependences. The <hi>Sultaneſs Valida,</hi> having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the ſecurity of her Son <hi>Soliman,</hi> took every day new Precautions to preſerve him
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46338:17"/>from the Snares, that might be laid for him. She gave him for his Guard five Thouſand of the braveſt <hi>Janiſaries</hi> of the Empire, and ſpar'd neither Care nor Coſt, to fix in his Service a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Experienc'd, Valiant, and Courageous Officers. As ſhe loſt not any opportunity of giving this dear Son faithful Servants, the Merit of <hi>Zouglan,</hi> and what ſhe dayly learn'd to his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, bred in her a deſire of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging him in the Service of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho it appears by all the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we have ſeen of the <hi>Serag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> that the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi>'s Apartment is inacceſſible to Men, <hi>Valida,</hi> who being a Woman of great Abilities, had for a long time govern'd the Empire, during the Minority of her Son <hi>Mahomet,</hi> now reigning, had acquir'd an
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46338:17"/>Authority, which no other <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſſes</hi> had ever had; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe took no great Care to ſubject her ſelf to the Cuſtom, or that the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who is not over violently inclin'd to Ladies, was not ſo Jealous of his <hi>Seraglio,</hi> as his Predeceſſors had been, it is certain, that <hi>Valida</hi> admitted Men into her Apartment without any Obſtacle. She ſent alſo for <hi>Zouglan,</hi> to propoſe to him the taking Engagements with her, and fixing himſelf in the Service of her Son <hi>Soliman,</hi> whoſe Guard of <hi>Janiſaries</hi> he ſhould Command.</p>
            <p>This Princeſs ſpake with ſo much Wit, and accompanied, whatever ſhe ſaid, with ſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able an Air, that it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſiſt her when ſhe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted any thing. <hi>Zouglan,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:46338:18"/>who knew, that <hi>Zaratima</hi> was with <hi>Valida,</hi> flattered himſelf, that the Relation, he ſhould have to the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> might facilitate to him the means of ſeeing this fair Perſon, and perhaps of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſome Mark of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement. At this view he promiſed <hi>Valida</hi> all ſhe would require of him. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> aſſur'd him, that ſhe would make him find ſo many Advantages, that he ſhould never have Cauſe to repent the Attachment, he had for her; and as her Addreſſes were very great, and that ſhe knew how to engage Men, by whatever might moſt ſenſibly touch them, ſhe ſhewed him a great number of fine Young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which were about her, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to underſtand, that ſhe took a Pleaſure in educating them to recompenſe thoſe, who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46338:18"/>ſhould ſerve her faithfully.</p>
            <p>All theſe Maids, who had heard <hi>Zouglan</hi> ſpoken of to <hi>Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> in very Advantageous Terms, teſtifi'd a Joy in ſeeing a Man of ſo great a Reputation. <hi>Zaratima</hi> did not at firſt comprehend, that <hi>Zouglan Cheitan</hi> was the ſame <hi>Zouglan,</hi> whoſe life ſhe had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and who had nevertheleſs ſo frankly put himſelf again into her Fathers Hands. Judge the greatneſs of her Joy, when ſhe came to know him. The Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhe felt, was ſo much the more real, as that ſhe imagined her ſelf to have a great ſhare in the glory he had gotten; ſhe alſo from that very Moment took a particular Intereſt in his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who eaſily ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her out, had not the leaſt Thought of caſting his Eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> other Maids,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46338:19"/>and letting <hi>Zaratima</hi> know by the Attention, with which he beheld her, that nothing could equal his Acknowledgement. He was about to unſay all he had promiſed <hi>Valida,</hi> and to tell her, that he could not enter into any manner of Engagement without the Participation of <hi>Zaratima,</hi> whoſe Right it was to diſpoſe of a Life, he ow'd to her Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but the Fear he had of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing this fair Perſon, hindred him, and he was obliged, by his Reſpect for <hi>Valida,</hi> to go forth at that very time, when his Eyes began to make <hi>Zaratima</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Sentiments of his Heart.</p>
            <p>He fail'd not to inform <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> of the Converſation he had with the <hi>Sultaneſs;</hi> but durſt not ſpeak to him of <hi>Zaratima,</hi> nor of all the Secret Motions, he felt in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46338:19"/>of that charming Perſon. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahim,</hi> who ſaw, that all the People, and even the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> bare a great Affection to <hi>Soliman,</hi> and who was very glad, if there ſhould happen any Revolution, to have a powerful Protector with that Prince, was not ſorry, that his Friend applyed himſelf to his Service; but was ſo far from deturning him, that he gave him new Reaſons to confirm him in his Reſolution. <hi>Zouglan</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs a great deal of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to remove from <hi>Adrianople,</hi> becauſe <hi>Zaratima</hi> dwelt there. In the mean time as he expected all things from <hi>Valida</hi>'s Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he imagined, that <hi>Zaratima</hi> might be the Recompence of the Services he ſhould do <hi>Soliman.</hi> This ſole Thought ſo agreeably flatter'd his Love and his Hopes, that no longer delaying his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46338:20"/>he was in a ſhort time after at <hi>Burſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Burſa</hi> was heretofore the ſeat of the <hi>Bithynian</hi> Kings, and is at this day the Appennage of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Princes, when they are ſo happy, as not to be Victims to the cruel Policy of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperors, who ordinarily cauſe their Brethren to be ſtrangled, to take away from the People all Pretexts of Sedition and Revolt. <hi>Soliman,</hi> who had a great many Perſons of Merit in his Service, led there a Life ſufficiently plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. His Revenue, which was already very conſiderable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed dayly by the care <hi>Valida</hi> took to give him whatever ſhe could handſomly lay up; and as his Place was one of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the Empire; he feared not being aſſaulted, ſince he was moreover aſſur'd both of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:46338:20"/>Peoples, and the <hi>Janizaries</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. In the mean time, tho he were in Condition to live at an height, ſuitable to his Quality, yet through the Counſel of his Mother, he was contented to live ſafe, and retir'd, not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling himſelf with Pomp, but always avoiding, whatever might give a jealouſie to his Brother, the <hi>Sultan. Soliman,</hi> who knew the Reputation of <hi>Zouglan,</hi> and was over and above particularly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of his Merit by the Letters of <hi>Valida,</hi> receiv'd him with all the Teſtimonies of eſteem he could expect from a great Prince. He alſo took a ſingular pleaſure in hearing him diſcourſe of Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary matters, and ſeveral times oblig'd him to give him a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Account of the Combats, in which he had been. <hi>Zouglan,</hi> loving only true Glory, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46338:21"/>ſeeking to ſhun the Fault, into which falſe <hi>Bravoes</hi> ordinarily fall, ſpake of all the Actions, he had ſeen, giving a thouſand Commendations to thoſe, that had accompany'd him, and ſcarce ever ſaying any thing of himſelf; which if he were at any time conſtrain'd to do, he attributed to Fortune the happy Succeſſes, that were due only to his Valor, and Courage. <hi>Soliman,</hi> who has a very delicate Wit, was ſo charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Modeſty, that it augmented the Eſteem, and good Opinion, he already had of him, and engaged him to give him all the Satisfactions he could expect in a Court, ſo peaceable, and limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zouglan</hi> had now been near ſix Months at <hi>Burſa,</hi> and was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſeeking ſome Pretence to make a Journey to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:46338:21"/>hopes to ſee there the fair <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima,</hi> when he received a Letter from <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> by which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him, that he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come paſſionately amorous of a very fair Perſon; that he had u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all indeavors to gain his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, without being able to effect it; that he had juſt learnt, how this ſame Perſon was return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her Parents, and that ſhe would paſs by <hi>Burſa,</hi> or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts; which obliged him to deſire <hi>Zouglan</hi> to keep his <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> in readineſs, that he might ſeize on her, and afterward ſend her back to him, the moſt ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he could, to <hi>Adrionaple,</hi> aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, that he could never do him a more agreeable Service. Thoſe, that know, how Cavalier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the <hi>Turks</hi> Act with Ladies, will not wonder at <hi>Ibrahim</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, which is not extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46338:22"/>for a <hi>Turk. Zouglan,</hi> who was very glad to have an Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of doing his Friend a Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſent <hi>Janiſaries</hi> into all Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, through which he judged <hi>Ibrahim</hi>'s Miſtreſs might paſs; and two days after he was advertiz'd, that ſhe had been ſtopt within three Leagues of <hi>Burſa.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were, that he might take all Meaſures neceſſary for the conducting her ſecretly, and without noiſe; or whether he was very deſirous to ſee that fair Perſon, which had wounded his Friends Heart, he went to the Place, where ſhe was; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaw her, he diſpoſed all things for her immediate depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and gave order, ſhe ſhould have notice to be in readineſs, not being willing to delay the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, his Friend might receive by the return of what he lov'd. He entered ſome time after into her
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46338:22"/>Chamber, where he found a Perſon in deſpair, that melted into Tears between the Arms of two Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which ſerved her. The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in which ſhe was, hindred him from obſerving her Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; but the diſconſolate La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cry'd out ſo loud at the ſight of him, that <hi>Zouglan</hi> was ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at it, and approach'd to view her a little nearer. The Lady ſav'd him from the Labor; for advancing towards him with Precipitation, ſhe call'd him Coward, Traytor, and Monſter of Ingratitude. <hi>Zouglan</hi> knew his fair <hi>Zaratima,</hi> and was ſo ſeiz'd with Sorrow, Joy, and a thouſand other confus'd Motions, that he continued a long time in a maze, not having the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſpeak one word to her. In fine being inconſolable for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given ſo much diſcontent to a Perſon, to whom he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46338:23"/>for his Life, he caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at her Feet, acknowledging, that he ſhould Merit all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches ſhe heapt upon him, were he guilty of any thing, but having had too much Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency for a Friend. He endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured conſequently to let her know, that, if he had been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertis'd of her Journey, he would not have fail'd being on the way to ſerve her, and receive her Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, adding, That he was not capable of ever being deficient in his reſpect to her; and to let her ſee, that ſhe alone poſſeſt all his thoughts, he told her farther, That he had ſo much indifference for all other Perſons in the World, that he would not go one ſtep to enjoy the faireſt Princeſs on the Earth. He preſented her his Friends Letter, beſeeching her to look into it, to the end it might the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:46338:23"/>better ſerve to juſtify what he told her. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> judging by <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Submiſſions, and the good opinion ſhe already had of him, that he ſpake ſincerely to her, found her ſelf leſs unhappy, than ſhe thought, for <hi>Zouglan</hi> was overjoy'd to ſee her Choler diſſipated, and went a little after forth of her Chamber, that being alone with her Women, ſhe might more eaſily recover out of the diſorder, in which he left her. As ſoon as he was alone, he made a thouſand Reflexions upon his adventure, which appear'd to him very ſingular. The remembrance, of what he ow'd to <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> put him at firſt in a great perplexity. It was difficult for him to reſolve to fail him. His particular Intereſt, and the Sentiments, he had for the fair <hi>Zaratima,</hi> appeared to him of too feeble importance, to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46338:24"/>hinder him from doing his Friend the Service, he expected from his cares. But when he repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to himſelf, what he ow'd to <hi>Zaratima,</hi> and made reflexion, That he ſhould never have known this Friend, had ſhe not given him the means by delivering him out of the danger he had been in, he no longer queſtion'd the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf on her ſide, believing, he embrac'd it only through a pure motive of acknowledgment. The Pleaſure he took in deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, making him ſhut his Eyes againſt the different mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, that ſhar'd in his Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he revok'd all the Orders, he had already given, and willing to draw ſome advantage from his Error, he magnificently treated <hi>Zaratima,</hi> cauſing her to be ſerv'd, with what ever could be found moſt rare in <hi>Bithynia.</hi> He after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46338:24"/>deſired her to give him leave to wait upon her to <hi>Temi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoüar</hi> with a Guard of five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> to ſecure her from all Attempts, her extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Beauty might inſpire into thoſe, that ſhould ſee her. <hi>Zaratima</hi> was ſo ſatisfied to ſee, that <hi>Zouglan</hi> gave not himſelf the Lye by any of his Actions, and that ſhe was not deceiv'd in the Advantageous Judgements, ſhe had made of him, that ſhe let him in fine underſtand, ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd his Care, and that he might aſſure himſelf, ſhe ſhould always be diſpos'd to render Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to his Merit. <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who had never dar'd ſpeak to her of his Love, acquainted her, that he had very paſſionate Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for her from the firſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſaw her, making uſe of the ſtrongeſt Expreſſions Love
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46338:25"/>could furniſh him with, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate to her, That his Life would be inſupportable to him without the hopes he had to employ it for her Service. <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratima,</hi> perſwaded of his Love, and mollified by theſe laſt words, ſpake to him in very obliging Terms. In the mean time ſhe forbad him going along with her, refuſing alſo the Guard, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered her; but <hi>Zouglan</hi> was too much intereſted in her ſafety, to let her go without being well attended. The Prohibition, ſhe had made him, was to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. He cauſed her to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by thirty <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> of whoſe Fidelity, and Valor he was aſſur'd, ordering them not to leave her, till ſhe was near <hi>Temiſoüar. Zaratima</hi> departed, very well ſatisfi'd with her Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Conduct, and ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:46338:25"/>diſpleaſed with his not having obey'd her, that the Care he had of making her be guarded, tho againſt her Will, finiſhed the convincing her of his Paſſion, and confirm'd her in the favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sentiments, ſhe already had for him: So true it is, That there are Occurrences, in which Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion paſſes with Ladies for Merit. <hi>Zouglan</hi> in the mean time was not a little diſquieted. The Letter, he had receiv'd from his Friend, oblig'd him to give him an Account of what he had done, and at the ſame time to ſet himſelf right in his Opinion; but not being able to reſolve on the making uſe of any Artifice, to diſguiſe the Truth to him, he choſe rather not to write. <hi>Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him</hi> ſome time after ſent him word that he believed he had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his Letter, ſince he made
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46338:26"/>him no Anſwer about a matter, for which he relyed on him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing throughly perſwaded, that he wanted not good Will to ſerve him, when Occaſion offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Zouglan,</hi> without deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any farther into particulars, anſwered him. That he did him Juſtice in holding himſelf aſſured of the Zeal, he had for his Intereſts.</p>
            <p>About this time dy'd the <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Valida,</hi> which wrought a great Change in the Affairs of the <hi>Port.</hi> The Miniſters, who fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, had very great Reſpects for her, not daring to decide any thing in important Matters, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out demanding her Advice. <hi>Kiſlar Agaſi</hi> governed within the <hi>Serag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and ſtood very fair in the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Opinion. <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> the <hi>Grand Viſier,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated all State Affairs. <hi>Ibrahim Caimacan</hi> had the Direction of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:46338:26"/>the Finances, ſubordinate to the <hi>Grand Viſier;</hi> and <hi>Soliman Aga,</hi> Maſter of the Horſe, was the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vado</hi> of the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Pleaſures, and kept a perfect Intelligence, with the other Miniſters. However, as they all knew the Addreſs of <hi>Valida,</hi> and were ſenſible, how great an Aſcendant ſhe had over the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi>'s Spirit, when ſhe would give her ſelf the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to cultivate it, they liv'd with great Circumſpection towards her, and teſtified to her abundance of Attachment and Reſpect, always fearing, ſhe would cauſe ſome Revolution in favor of her ſecond Son <hi>Soliman;</hi> but after the Death of that <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> they no longer kept Meaſures with this Prince. His Party became in a little time very weak; and as he had not any Relation with the Miniſters, to advance his Creatures, the moſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46338:27"/>part abandoned him to follow the Grand <hi>Viſier.</hi> There was ſoon after a Diſcourſe of War; and <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> who, during the Life of <hi>Valida,</hi> durſt not ſtir from the <hi>Port,</hi> declar'd, That at the beginning of the Spring he would go into the Campaign at the Head of a powerful Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who was accuſtomed to the Fatigues of War, and to lead a Tumultuous Life, very oppoſite to the Tranquillity, in which he was with <hi>Soliman,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of ſeeing his Miſtreſs, and far from Opportunities of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Glory, fell into a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment, which dayly decayed his Health. His Generoſity, and the Remembrance, of what he had promiſed <hi>Valida,</hi> obliged him to force his Temper, and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all the Incommodities, which the Violence, he did himſelf, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:46338:27"/>inevitable to him; but the Rumors of War, which were ſpread about on every ſide, awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his firſt Ardor, and gave him new Inquietudes. He repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to himſelf, that being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in the Service of <hi>Soliman,</hi> he could not abandon that Prince, without offending his Honor, and particularly, ſince it was every where ſaid, That the vaſt Deſigns of <hi>Valida</hi> would come to nothing, and that this Reaſon had already made <hi>Soliman</hi> loſe many of his Creatures. <hi>Zouglan</hi> was continually tormented with theſe Reflexions, not being able to reſolve either upon living any longer without the ſight of his Miſtreſs, or upon quitting the Service of <hi>Soliman.</hi> He was aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Idleneſs, he lived in at a time, when the whole <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire was preparing for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:46338:28"/>War. <hi>Zaratima</hi> continually came into his Mind, his Love reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched him with his Lazineſs, and he ſeem'd to himſelf unworthy to Love ſo fair a Perſon, ſince he was able to live ſo long away from her. The greatneſs of his Courage, and the Attachment, he had for <hi>Soliman,</hi> combated theſe Sentiments, and he would perhaps have dyed without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any Reſolution, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with his Perplexities, if the Prince himſelf had not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved his Melancholy, which the Change of his Countenance ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred but too viſible. This obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to ask the Cauſe of it. <hi>Zouglan</hi> was uncapable to make uſe of any Artifice. He could not therefore conceal from the Prince, how he felt himſelf of too ſtirring a Temper to accommode himſelf to a quiet Life, and that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:46338:28"/>the Rumors of War, which were diſperſt about, had made ſo ſtrong an Impreſſion on his Mind, that he was neceſſitated to call his Duty to Succor, and to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber himſelf of the inviolable At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment, he had ſworn to his Service, to be able to reſiſt it. <hi>Soliman,</hi> who was perſuaded of <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s ſincerity, and who could not diſapprove of ſuch Noble Sentiments, teſtifyed, That it would be very diſpleaſant to him to loſe him, but yet that he had rather conſent to his Departure, than deprive the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire of a Man of his Merit, who was in Condition to do the <hi>Sultan</hi> important Services. <hi>Zouglan,</hi> touch'd with the Prince's Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, defended himſelf a long time from accepting the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion he gave him to depart; but <hi>Soliman</hi> having let him know,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:46338:29"/>that he was ſo far from not being content with it, that he would abſolutely have him make uſe of the Occaſion, which preſented it ſelf, <hi>Zouglan</hi> kiſt the Hem of his Garment, aſſuring him, that he would be no leſs his in the Army, than at <hi>Burſa,</hi> ſince he regarded the Empire, as a good, which might one day appertain to him, and that he ſhould believe he ſtill ſerv'd him, whil'ſt he was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring to extend the Limits of that ſame Empire, in which he had ſo great a ſhare. <hi>Soliman</hi> was the firſt to haſten his departure, that he might go ſollicit Employs at the <hi>Port,</hi> before the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> had diſpoſed of them, and to ſhew the Satisfaction, he had in his Services, he made him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Preſents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zouglan,</hi> being arrived at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drianople,</hi> gave an account to <hi>Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:46338:29"/>Caimacam,</hi> his Protector and Friend, of all, that had paſſed between him and <hi>Soliman,</hi> and in what manner he retired from that Prince; but always avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpeaking to him of <hi>Zaratima.</hi> He deſir'd him afterwards to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his Credit with the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> to get him employ'd in the War, he deſign'd againſt the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> This Miniſter, who alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy bragg'd of exterminating all the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> would himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone have the whole Glory of that War, and therefore know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Reputation, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, that, if he ſhould make uſe of his Service, the Publick would attribute to him the good Succeſs of the War. This Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon oblig'd him to reject the <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macan</hi>'s Propoſition; but <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> who had abundance of Wit, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating the Cauſe of this Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, propos'd a new to the Grand
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:46338:30"/>
               <hi>Viſier,</hi> the employing of <hi>Zouglan</hi> upon the Frontiers of <hi>Perſia.</hi> The <hi>Viſier</hi> promis'd to ſatisfie him; but withal told him, That he could not ſend any Troops to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Aſia,</hi> till he had firſt ſeen, whether thoſe, he deſign'd for <hi>Europe,</hi> were compleat. The <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macan</hi> was contented with this Anſwer, of which he advertiz'd his Friend, who was mean while in great Impatience to ſee his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. Judging therefore, that the Troops, which were levying in ſo great number through the whole extent of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, could not be ready of a long time, he reſolv'd to take advantage of this Interval for the making a Journey to the place of <hi>Zaratima</hi>'s abode. Having told the <hi>Caimacan,</hi> that he was going to divert himſelf in the Country, he repaired with great diligence to <hi>Temiſoüar,</hi> to endeavor there
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:46338:30"/>the ſeeing of this fair Perſon. Tho' the <hi>Turks</hi> never quit the <hi>Turban,</hi> Love, which works many other Miracles, and the Difficulties <hi>Zouglan</hi> foreſaw, he might meet with in ſeeing his Miſtreſs, made him reſolve to diſguiſe himſelf like a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and to put on a Peruke, and an Hat; and ſince it very often happens, that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Cavaliers, travelling into the Lands under the Grand <hi>Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi>'s Obedience, carry, without being Merchants, many Curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with which they furniſh themſelves in <hi>Europe,</hi> to make uſe of an Occaſion, <hi>Zouglan</hi> made Proviſion of theſe ſorts of Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſities at <hi>Belgrade,</hi> particularly of Stones, ſet in work with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Perfection. He gave ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally to all thoſe, who could facilitate the ſucceſs of his Deſign, that he was without any difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty introduc'd to <hi>Zaratima,</hi> under
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:46338:31"/>pretence of ſhewing her his choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Rareties. He took Care to diſguiſe his Voice, feigning, That with much difficulty he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Language. All theſe Precautions ſo well deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his fair Miſtreſs, that ſhe did not know him. She admir'd the Jewels, and thought only of cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch, as ſhe moſt fancy'd. Having ſet aſide many pieces, that pleas'd her, ſhe ask'd their price: The Stranger anſwered her, That he was not skill'd in the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant's Trade. This Anſwer trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who already fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his taking back the Jewels, ſhe had choſen; but the counterfeit <hi>Chriſtian</hi> told her, ſhe might keep them, and that he would take others in Exchange, or whatever ſhe pleas'd to give him. <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima,</hi> who had many old Pieces, of which ſhe made no uſe, was glad to find a man of ſo Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:46338:31"/>a Commerce; but what more ſurpriz'd her, was the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers Eaſineſs, who contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with an old Ruby, and ſome other Trifles, for many Jewels, ſhe had taken, which were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly fair. He offer'd alſo, if ſhe thought good, to bring her on the morrow ſome other very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things. <hi>Zaratima</hi> gave him leave to come again, telling him, he would oblige her in letting her ſee, whatever he had, that was curious. He retir'd, having had the Satisfaction to be ſome time with this amiable Perſon, and to get her to accept of ſome Preſents, which her Scrupuloſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would have cauſed her to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, had they been made her in any other way. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> tho very well skill'd in Jewels, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſted nevertheleſs her own Judgment in this rencounter, wherefore ſhe ſent for a <hi>Jeweſs,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:46338:32"/>that was verſt in this ſort of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick. The little, which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Merchant had taken in Exchange, for what he left her, made her fear, he had cheated her, and that the Stones ſhe had of him were falſe; but the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſs</hi> aſſur'd her, they were right, and even of greater Value, than ſhe thought for. All theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances redoubled her amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſhe was impatient to ſee this Man again, who ſet ſo little by things, that appear'd to her of ſo great Price. <hi>Zouglan</hi> had too much love, to forget, what he had promis'd her. He came again on the morrow, and preſented her with new Jewels. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> after ſhe had for a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſidered them, fix'd her Eye with an entire Attention up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, that brought them. She examin'd his Features, and his Voice, which he endeavoured to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:46338:32"/>diſguiſe, hinder'd her not from finding under an Habit, ſo little ſuitable to a <hi>Turk,</hi> what the day before ſhe had been ſo far from ſeeking. It was difficult for her to reſiſt the firſt Tranſports of Joy, which this agreeable ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe caus'd in her; but fearing, leſt ſome Motion of Tenderneſs might eſcape from her in preſence of her Women, ſhe dexterouſly rid her ſelf of thoſe, that were about her, and then manifeſted to <hi>Zouglan</hi> the ſenſible Pleaſure, ſhe receiv'd from the obliging manner, he had found out of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying to her his Love. They gave one another, a mutual Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Affairs, and <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> told <hi>Zaratima,</hi> he could not reſolve on his departure to go and command the Troops on the ſide of <hi>Aſia,</hi> without firſt taking leave of her <hi>Zaratima</hi> was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicted, that they were to be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:46338:33"/>ſo remote one from the other, but he aſſur'd her, that after the Succeſs of this Compaign, of which the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> promis'd himſelf ſo great Advantages, he would demand ſome employ in <hi>Europe,</hi> proteſting to her, that in what State ſoever his Fortune ſhould be, he would ſeek only to merit her Eſteem, and to do ſome Action, which might render him worthy of her. <hi>Zaratima</hi> conjur'd him, no more to expoſe himſelf to ſo many hazards, ſince he had already given Proofs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of his Valor. Their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation was very tender: <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> gave her his Word to return to her, aſſoon as ever his Honor could permit it; and <hi>Zaratima,</hi> after ſhe had aſſur'd him of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vows inceſſantly for his ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy return, promis'd him, on her ſide, that nothing ſhould be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to diminiſh the Sentiments
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:46338:33"/>of Tenderneſs, of which ſhe would have him reſt ſecure. One of her Women coming back, hinder'd their proceeding, and they no longer ſpake of any thing, but the Stones. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who would not propoſe the giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him back the Preſent, he had made her with ſo much Addreſs, preſented him with a Bracelet of her Hair. He receiv'd it with a great deal of Pleaſure, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in preſence of his Miſtreſs's Women, that ſuch Works were very rare in his Country. Tho the time preſſed him, he having none to loſe, that he might ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at <hi>Adrianople</hi> before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the Troops; yet was it impoſſible for him to reſolve upon removing from <hi>Zaratima,</hi> without making her a third Viſit. They gave one another recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Aſſurances of ever continuing in a mutual Love, affirming,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:46338:34"/>they ſhould never have happy Moments, whilſt diſtance of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces depriv'd them of the Joy of ſeeing each other; but <hi>Zaratima</hi> who was very tender, foreſeeing, that her Tears might betray her in the preſence of her Women, left <hi>Zouglan,</hi> without having the Power to bid him adieu, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing privately withdrawn, ſhe caus'd him a moment after to be advertiz'd, that he ſhould take back his Jewels. He departed on the morrow, haſting with extream diligence to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> where he found <hi>Ibrahim</hi> in very great pain for him; becauſe the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> who had already made his Army March, would have him Aſſemble all the <hi>Militia,</hi> he could raiſe, and form a Camp of them, to Guard the Frontiers of the Empire, lying toward, <hi>Perſia. Zouglan,</hi> after he had made his Acknowledgement to the <hi>Caima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:46338:34"/>put himſelf in Condition to execute the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s Orders, and having aſſembled the <hi>Militia,</hi> which he found in very great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, he joyned them to a ſmall Body of regulated Troops, that his Friend <hi>Ibrahim</hi> had caus'd to be given him. 'Twas time he ſhould be on his March, ſince the <hi>Perſians</hi> began to appear, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, they might without fear ravage the Provinces of this Neighborhood. He not only drove them from the Frontiers of the Empire, but entered alſo into their Country, hinder'd them from keeping the Field, and made himſelf Maſter of the Province of <hi>Serüan,</hi> which he abandon'd, after he had taken Meaſures to render it tributary to the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Zouglan</hi> made War with ſo advantageous a Succeſs, the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> who was at the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46338:35"/>head of two hundred Thouſand Men, threatned all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and had alſo beſieg'd <hi>Vienna,</hi> which is the Metropolis of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and the ſeat of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperors. But as the hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of numerous Troops is not enough to make one Succeed in his Enterpriſes, there being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd alſo an Head, who has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, Valor, and Conduct, the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> took his Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſo ill, or perhaps, to ſpeak more juſtly, the Beſieged defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves with ſo much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that they gave the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Army, tho very weak, time to come to their Aſſiſtance, and to appear upon the Hills about <hi>Vienna.</hi> This ſo aſtoniſh'd the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> that conſulting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his own Fear, he ſhamefully rais'd the Siege. All the World knows, that, to retreat with the leſs danger, he abandon'd his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:46338:35"/>Baggage, and Sacrific'd to the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Reſentment five hundred <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> that guarded the <hi>Trenches;</hi> which hindred not his being purſu'd by the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and <hi>Polonians,</hi> who pilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, what Baggage was left him, defeated his Reer, and carried off a very great Number of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners. Amidſt the Vexation of ſo much ill Succeſs the <hi>Viſier</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got nothing, that might preſerve him the good Will of the <hi>Sultan,</hi> his Maſter, with which he held himſelf aſſur'd to repair all he had left. In this Deſign he gave him account of all things with great Exactneſs, but in ſo dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a Manner, that he caſt all the Infellicities of this Compaign upon the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Buda,</hi> and Count <hi>Tekely,</hi> whom he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor'd to render ſuſpected to the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> by accuſing him of Intelligence with the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:46338:36"/>His Artifice ſucceeded to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. The Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> teſtified, that he was very well ſatisfi'd with his Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s Conduct, and ſent him alſo a great Standard with all the Marks of Eſteem, and Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this Miniſter could have hop'd for, had he taken <hi>Vienna.</hi> In the mean time the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> gaining dayly new Advantages o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the Grand <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier</hi> not making any Motion to repel them, they began ſecretly to murmur againſt him at <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople:</hi> And Count <hi>Tekely,</hi> who was wont to receive great Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from the <hi>Port,</hi> having about the <hi>Sultan</hi> Spies, which gave him notice of all, that paſs'd, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he had been render'd ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious to the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> and that they ſpake no more of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the uſual Aids, forgot not to juſtifie himſelf by Letters;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46338:36"/>but it was in Vain. His Letters did not undeceive the Miniſters of the <hi>Port,</hi> who remain'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that he held Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the <hi>Germans. Tekely,</hi> ſeeing no Medium between being ruin'd, or juſtifi'd, took a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution extreamly dangerous. He went himſelf <hi>incognito</hi> to the <hi>Port,</hi> and having found Means, by the Credit of the <hi>Kiſlar Agaſi,</hi> who was his particular Friend, to have an Audience of the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> before whom he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated himſelf with his Face to the Ground, he told him, that he brought him his Head, choſing rather to loſe it, than to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Calumnies of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and the disfavor of his Lord and Protector. <hi>Tekely</hi>'s Boldneſs was happily ſucceſsful to him. The <hi>Sultan</hi> heard his Reaſons, and judg'd by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cital, he made him, that all the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:46338:37"/>Misfortunes, arriv'd during the fiege, ought to be imputed to the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s ill Conduct. He permitted <hi>Tekely</hi> to return, aſſuring him of the Protection, he demanded, and engaging to ſend him ſuch powerful Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that he ſhould ſoon be in Condition to repair with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage all the loſſes, he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd. They began afreſh to make Complaints againſt the <hi>Viſier.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one blam'd him, and no body was any longer afraid to decry his Conduct, againſt which they murmur'd publickly. <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlar Agaſi,</hi> who had a long time expected an opportunity to do the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> ill Offices, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Sultan</hi> favorably diſpos'd to hear all, that was ſaid againſt him, inform'd him of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, that were made openly, and having acquainted him with the particulars of the Advantages,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:46338:37"/>the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had newly gain'd over the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Troops through the <hi>Viſier</hi>'s Sole negligence, he let him underſtand, it was to be fear'd, that the hatred, which not only the People, but the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaries</hi> alſo, bore this Miniſter, might give Occaſion to a general revolt. The <hi>Sultan,</hi> who ſince his Converſation with <hi>Tekely,</hi> was already much prepoſſeſt againſt <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> determin'd, tho with difficulty enough, to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice him to the publick Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and diſpatch'd two <hi>Agaes,</hi> who went to <hi>Belgrade,</hi> where he was, and cut off his Head.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Viſier</hi>'s Death gave a new Face to the Affairs of the Empire. The Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> who got ſixteen Millions by it, refus'd to give conſent, they ſhould be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in paying the Troops, and re-eſtabliſhing the Affairs of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> altho the whole <hi>Divan</hi> was
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:46338:38"/>of that Opinion. He alſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately perſiſted in not permitting his Treaſure, which is the great Spring of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperors, to be open'd, anſwering thoſe, who repreſented him the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, there was of opening it, to remedy the Diſorder, there was in Affairs, that they muſt make uſe of the ordinary Revenues; and if they were not ſufficient to reſettle all things, it was for his Council to find other Funds, to ſupply the defect. The <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Humor, and the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they foreſaw, there would be in bringing the Affairs of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire again into a good State, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated the Eagerneſs of thoſe, that had Right of pretending to the Office of Grand <hi>Viſier.</hi> The <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlar Agaſi,</hi> who had alway a great deal of Credit, and who imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, tho without any Ground; that the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> thought
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46338:38"/>of putting him into this Poſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd before hand, that he would not accept this great Charge, well knowing, he had not Capacity enough to ſupport the Burthen, of it. <hi>Soliman Aga,</hi> Maſter of the Horſe, who was the Grand <hi>Senior</hi>'s true Favorite, judging, he ſhould always be powerful e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, as long as he had his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Favor, told the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who offer'd to make him Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> that all his Ambition was to pleaſe him, and that he much more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ſolely attach'd to his Perſon, than to ſhare his Cares between the Prince, and the State, as he ſhould be obliged to do, if he accepted the Charge, with which he would honor him. So obliging a Refuſal augmented the Eſteem, and Affection, the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> had for him, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd him to name for Grand <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, Ibrahim Aga,</hi> who before was <hi>Caimacan.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:46338:39"/>
            <p>In the mean time there came Advice, that the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who dayly made new Progreſſes in <hi>Hungary,</hi> had beſieged <hi>Vicegrade.</hi> The decay of Affairs obliged the Grand <hi>Viſter</hi> often to affemble the <hi>Divan,</hi> to reſolve on the means of breaking the Effect of this Enterpriſe. Many Expedients were propos'd; but the new Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> was of Opinion to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Frontiers of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and aſſerting, that his Predeceſſor <hi>Muſtapha</hi> had unjuſtly declar'd War againſt the <hi>Germans,</hi> he concluded it much more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to turn their Arms againſt the <hi>Polonians,</hi> who had without any Reaſon broken the Truce, which the redoubtable <hi>Port</hi> had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. The <hi>Sultan,</hi> who had promis'd <hi>Tekely,</hi> he would never abandon him, was of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sentiment to the Grand <hi>Viſier;</hi> which hinder'd not this Miniſter
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:46338:39"/>from bringing other Reaſons for to ſupport his firſt Opinion. This was to reſiſt the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Pleaſure, which made him enter into ſo great a Fury againſt him, that he roſe up with a Deſign to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him. He pardon'd him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs at the Petition of his Favorite <hi>Soliman,</hi> and this Affair, gave Occaſion to the report, which at that time ran through all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> that the new Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> was ſtrangl'd.</p>
            <p>There arrived at that time a Courier at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> by whom they underſtood, That the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had taken <hi>Vicegradt;</hi> that <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> who advanc'd to relieve that Place, had been bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and that in this diſpute the <hi>Turks</hi> had loſt eight hundred <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> ſeveral Colors, and the greateſt part of their Canon. They learn'd almoſt at the ſame time that the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:46338:40"/>Prince of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> taking advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Diſorder, the <hi>Turks</hi> were in, had attack'd <hi>Weitzen,</hi> a Place ſituated upon one of the Arms of the <hi>Danow,</hi> which form the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> and that the Garriſon, terrifi'd by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the <hi>Turks</hi> defeat, has made but a very weak Reſiſtance, yielding upon Diſcretion, tho it was compos'd of five hundred <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> commanded by an <hi>Aga,</hi> who were all made Priſoners of War, and ſent to <hi>Gran.</hi> This ill News augmented the Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Affairs at the <hi>Port.</hi> But the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> who conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually look'd with contempt on all, he learn'd of the Progreſs, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> made in <hi>Hungary,</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf neither at the loſs of <hi>Weitzen,</hi> nor the defeat of his Troops; but went a Hunting on the ſide of the black Foreſt, with ſo much earneſtneſs, that he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:46338:40"/>ſeveral days without unclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing himſelf. The Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> who ſaw himſelf alone charg'd with the Conduct of the State, forbore not laboring with a great deal of Application, to prevent the Ruin, which ſeem'd to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. War, being the moſt important Affair of his Miniſtry, he who had no Deſign of removing from the <hi>Port,</hi> to put himſelf at the head of an Army, reſolv'd to give this employ to <hi>Zouglan,</hi> whom he regarded as his other ſelf, and whom he had already ſent for to be near him; but well knowing, that the Generals of Armies oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en loſe good Occaſions, becauſe they dare not hazard the Events of Affairs without particular Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the Prince, he deſir'd, <hi>Zouglan,</hi> whoſe Fidelity and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor were known to him, ſhould have a general Power, which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:46338:41"/>might ſet him above Governors, <hi>Baſſa's,</hi> and <hi>Berglerbegs</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Now ſince among the <hi>Turks,</hi> the Grand <hi>Viſiers</hi> alone are in Poſſeſſion of this Deſpotick Authority, he expected the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi>'s return, to get his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to a Project, he was medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in favor of his Friend.</p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly impatient to paſs again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hungary,</hi> that he might ſee his Miſtreſs, expected the Effect of the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s good Will, <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratima</hi> was in continual Alarms, and haſten'd by her Deſires the happy time of his Return. <hi>Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan Baſſa,</hi> who after the Death of <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> had the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Command in <hi>Hungary,</hi> being inform'd of <hi>Selim</hi>'s great Wealth, and of the Deſign, he had to give it his Daughter at her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, reſolved not to loſe ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorable an opportunity of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:46338:41"/>it to himſelf, with the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of a very fair Lady. In proſpect of this he ſought a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accommodation with <hi>Selim,</hi> after which he ſhew'd him all the ſigns of Conſideration and Eſteem he could deſire, not taking any Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in matters of War, without demanding his Advice. <hi>Selim</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of this General's kind Uſage, and perſwaded he would conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to Command in <hi>Hungary,</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, as a mark of his Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, to give him his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with all his Eſtate. <hi>Cabſtan,</hi> glad of his having been prevented by <hi>Selim</hi>'s Offers, embrac't him with the Teſtimonies of a very ſtrict Amity. From that time he always call'd him his Father, and they remain'd of accord, that the <hi>Baſſa</hi> ſhould eſpouſe <hi>Zaratima,</hi> as ſoon as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Army, which gave him a great deal of Diſquiet, ſhould have manifeſted
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:46338:42"/>their Deſign, either by their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, or by their Sitting down before ſome one of the Places which were menac'd. <hi>Selim</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd his Daughter of the Honor the <hi>Baſſa</hi> would do her, and of the Meaſures they had already taken together upon this Alliance. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> ſurpriz'd and troubled at ſo precipitate an Engagement, conjur'd her Father not to preſs her Marriage; but to be pleas'd, ſhe might continue ſome time longer with him. But <hi>Selim,</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to his Daughters Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, all the Reaſons ſhe gave him to oblige him to grant her the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, ſhe deſir'd, told her, without being toucht with her Tears, That as ſoon as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd, he would put her into the <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s Hands. This cruel Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſenſibly afflicted <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who, tho ſhe were determin'd to expel all ſorts of Extremities, even
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:46338:42"/>Death it ſelf, if it were Neceſſary, rather than prove falſe to <hi>Zouglan,</hi> yet fail'd not to ſend him a Perſon in whom ſhe confided, with order to put into his hands the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Billet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HAſten your Departure, if you ſtill love me: my Father is reſolv'd to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me to</hi> Cabſtan Baſſa, <hi>and tho I can anſwer you for my Heart, I fear all from ſo Potent a Man, ſupported by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a Father: for, methinks, the Death, I ſhould without delay give my ſelf, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his Violence, would be but a ſad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> who was on his return to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> learnt at his arrival there, that the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> daily made new Conqueſts upon him, and that there was ſo general a Dread amongſt the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Troops, that upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, which was ſpread abroad, of Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s having a Deſign to Beſiege <hi>Peſt,</hi> the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon had abandon'd that Place,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:46338:43"/>after they had ſet it on Fire, and were retir'd with diligence to to <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Diſorder of Affairs in <hi>Hungary</hi> for the advancement of his Friend, procur'd of the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> in favor of <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> the reviving the Office of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier,</hi> which had been ſeveral years ſuppreſt, being much like that of Conſtable in <hi>France. Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> was preparing to paſs into <hi>Hungary,</hi> to Command there with ſo reſplendent a Dignity, when he receiv'd <hi>Zaratima</hi>'s Billet. He was ready to die with Grief, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that his moſt cruel Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was going to deprive him of his Miſtreſs at the time, when he found himſelf in Condition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand her of her Father, without danger of being refus'd. Had he follow'd the Motions of his Love and of his Courage, he would
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:46338:43"/>have parted immediately to go to his dear <hi>Zaratima;</hi> but his new Dignity oblig'd him to manage himſelf, and to take other Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures before his Departure. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, ſince he was not ſenſible of the Greatneſs of his Fortune, but through Relation to his Love, preferring his fair Miſtreſs before all the Goods of the Earth, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to put his Mind in repoſe, and obtain'd upon other Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, an Order from the Grand <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier</hi> for Arreſting <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> and cauſing him to be conducted to the Caſtle of <hi>Zighet.</hi> He after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards finiſht the Regulation of his Affairs with all the ſpeed he could, and parted ſoon after from <hi>Adrianople</hi> to repair to <hi>Belgrads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whil'ſt he was in his March, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who had a Deſign to Beſiege <hi>Buda,</hi> caus'd a Bridge of Boats to be built over the <hi>Danow,</hi> in the place
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:46338:44"/>where that River is ſeparated into two Arms, which form the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> The Bridge being finiſht the Tenth of <hi>July,</hi> 1684. the Imperial Troops paſs'd thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame day in very good Order. The <hi>Turks,</hi> who had not been able to imagin, that the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> durſt attack <hi>Buda,</hi> charg'd very vigorouſly the Vauntguard of the Imperial Army, perſwaded, that it was only a Detachment; but they ſoon knew, they had to do with the whole Army; which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd them to retire in diſorder, and with the Loſs of a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their Men, which were ſlain by the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> Artillery. In the mean time the Count <hi>de Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberg,</hi> Mareſchal General of the Camp, approacht <hi>Buda,</hi> ſetting men to work on the Preparatives, neceſſary for the Siege. The <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts</hi> at firſt poſſeſt themſelves of the <hi>Fauxbourgs,</hi> maugre the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:46338:44"/>great Fire, thoſe of the Place made to hinder them. Three days after the <hi>Turks</hi> ſet the Lower Town on Fire, retiring themſelves into the Upper, which is defended by a well-fortify'd Caſtle. The ſame day the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> began to play their Canon, and made themſelves Maſters of the firſt Ditch, and of Mount <hi>St. Gerard,</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Town. On the Twenty ſecond the <hi>Turks</hi> made a vigorous Sally, in which they loſt a great many Men, and kill'd Four hundred of the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</hi> Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> having learnt at that time that the <hi>Turks</hi> were aſſembling the Body of an Army about <hi>Hanſchabec,</hi> leaving Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> Foot and Horſe, neceſſary to continue the Siege, marcht all the Night with the reſt of the Horſe, and a thouſand Foot. He came by break of day within half a League of the <hi>Turks</hi> Camp, in a place, whence he might plainly diſcover them. He judg'd them to be about Twenty thouſand Men, and ſaw them make Motions, which caus'd him to believe they had advice of his March. They would have faln on the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> Flank, but they found every where
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:46338:45"/>a great Reſiſtance, and Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> charg'd them ſo home, and with ſo much Succeſs, that the <hi>Turks</hi> were oblig'd to make a furious Retreat. The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> kill'd them above Four thouſand Men upon the place, wounded a great number, and took many Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The <hi>Turks</hi> loſt alſo all their Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and their Canon. Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> return'd again before <hi>Buda,</hi> and having acquainted the Beſieged with the Advantages he had gain'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Turks,</hi> ſummon'd them to yield; but they teſtify'd by their Anſwer, That they were reſolved to defend themſelves to the utmoſt extremity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who already knew of the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> was at his arrival at <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade</hi> inform'd of the <hi>Turks</hi> Defeat, and of the great Conſternation all their Troops were in. He apply'd himſelf with extraordinary care to give order for all things; and the ſole Hope of ſpeedily ſeeing his Miſtreſs, comforted him for the ill Condition, in which he found all the Affairs of <hi>Hungary.</hi> He was already preparing himſelf to go to her, whil'ſt the Troops, he deſtin'd for the Relief of <hi>Buda,</hi> were drawing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:46338:45"/>when he learnt, that <hi>Cara Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in <hi>Buda,</hi> being ſick at the time, he was advertiz'd that the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> thought to attack him, had ſent order to <hi>Selim, Diſdar</hi> or Governor of <hi>Temiſouar,</hi> of whoſe Valor and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience he was ſatisfy'd, to come and aſſiſt him with his Counſels, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Place, if his Sickneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd; and that the <hi>Diſdar,</hi> to anſwer the <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s Confidence, and ſhew him that he fear'd not the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> was gone to join him, having taken with him whatever he had moſt precious, and alſo his Daughter <hi>Zaratima,</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhe would be in greater Security with him, than any where elſe. This News was not a little diſpleaſing to the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who ſaw his Hopes fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by it, and his Miſtreſs expos'd to all the Perils and Incommodities, that are ſuffer'd in a Beſieged Town. This Reaſon augmented the Hatred, he already had for the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and made him redouble his Cares ſpeedily to relieve the Place. He wrote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> to acquaint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the State of Affairs, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:46338:46"/>him new Succors. He ſent Couriers on all ſides, to preſs the March of the Troops, he would aſſemble. He viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the Places, to the end he might ſee, whether he could not draw out a Party from the Garriſons, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to be aſſaulted, and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted alſo ſtore of Money, to make Recruits. His great Reputation, his Liberalities, and the Confidence, that appear'd in all his Actions, greatly contributed to raiſe the fallen Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Troops. In the mean time, tho he were a Man of very great Merit, the Newneſs of his Office of <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> fail'd not to impoſe upon the People, who were ſo prepoſſeſt in his favor, that they ſpake of him as the Reſtorer of the Empires Affairs, even before he had attempted any thing. Being arriv'd at <hi>Zighet,</hi> he went to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa</hi> in his Priſon, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving askt him, whether he knew him, the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> who was already inform'd of his Advancement, and perſwaded he would cauſe him to be Strangled, anſwer'd him fiercely, That he muſt not expect to ſee him guilty of ſo much Mean-ſpiritedneſs, as to ask him a Life,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:46338:46"/>he well knew, he had reſolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of, as himſelf would not have fail'd to treat him in the ſame manner, had he not eſcap'd from him at <hi>Temiſouar;</hi> but that Fortune having diſpos'd it otherwiſe, it was reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he ſhould be puniſht, ſince he was the moſt unfortunate. The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> ſurpriz'd at ſo haughty an Anſwer, and ſo beſeeming a Man of War, gave him his hand, and told him, That the only Revenge he would take of him, was to deſire his Amity, and to give him the Command of an Army, for to put a great Convoy into <hi>Caminiec,</hi> and to oppoſe the Attempts the <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> might make upon that Place. He would not ſo much as require of him any Condition, as to oblige him to think no more of <hi>Zaratima,</hi> being throughly perſwaded, that his Love and his Fortune would cauſe him to be preferr'd before his Rivals. <hi>Cabſtan,</hi> confounded at the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, kiſs'd the Hem of his Garment, aſſuring him; he ſhould have an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Acknowledgment of the Favor he did him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> being departed from
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:46338:47"/>
               <hi>Zighet</hi> to go to <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> learnt by the way that he muſt no longer expect to receive any Succor from the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Poſſega:</hi> becauſe Count <hi>Leſly</hi> at the Head of an Army, he had rais'd in <hi>Croatia,</hi> had beſieged the Fortreſs of <hi>Wierovitza,</hi> the taking of which facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated that of the Bridge of <hi>Eſſeck:</hi> which had oblig'd the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Poſſega,</hi> who knew of what Importance the conſervation of that Fortreſs was to them, to draw together all the Troops that were in the neighbouring Places, and to endeavor the Relief of <hi>Wiere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitza;</hi> but that the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> had repell'd him, and conſtrain'd him to retire, after he had loſt the greateſt part of his Troops: which had ſo much intimidated the Garriſon of <hi>Wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovitza,</hi> that they had Surrendred on the ſingle Summons of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> General. The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> was ſenſibly afflicted at this ill News. He learnt others at his arrival at <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> which comforted him for the loſs of <hi>Wierovitza:</hi> for he had advice, That <hi>Cara Mahomet Baſſa,</hi> who commanded in <hi>Buda,</hi> was perfectly recover'd, ſince the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had beſieg'd his Place;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:46338:47"/>That he wanted neither Victuals, nor Ammunitions; That he had Seven thouſand Men of the old Troops, not counting the Inhabitants and <hi>Jews,</hi> who did almoſt as much Service as the Souldiers; and in fine, that he made vigorous Sallies, which much incommoded the Beſiegers. Theſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices made the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> judge, he ſhould have time to get together Troops, ſufficient to relieve the Place; but when he made reflexion on the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes of his Miſtreſs, who was in a beſieged Town, and had not of a very long time heard from him, he was aſham'd, he had ſo long delay'd to let her know his Arrival, and determin'd immediately to write her the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Billet.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Was come to be near you, with a Deſign of never parting from you. I learnt at my arrival, you were at</hi> Buda <hi>with your Father, and that the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged that Place. I will never pardon them the ſenſible diſcontent, they have given me, in depriving me of the Pleaſure to ſee you, to ſpeak to you of my Love, and to give you account of all, I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:46338:48"/>being away from you. I hope to puniſh theſe Infidels, and to make them experiment, what a man can do, who at the ſame time ſerves his Prince, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends what he loves. I alſo flatter my ſelf, that your Father will put ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between</hi> Cabſtan <hi>and me, and that he will not find me altogether unworthy of you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>He would not ſend her word of his new Dignity of <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> either through Modeſty, or perhaps to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize her more agreeably, when he ſhould ſee her. He forbad alſo a dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Renegado, who was got out of <hi>Buda,</hi> and who undertook to return thither, to tell <hi>Zaratima</hi> that it was the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who gave him that Billet. His Love hindred him not from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of this Occaſion to exhort <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Mahomet</hi> to a ſedulous Performance of his Devoir, telling him, that he had already given an account to the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> of the Reſolution, he teſtify'd to make a good Defence of his Place; that he could aſſure him, he ſhould ſoon be reliev'd; but that he pray'd him to remember, that, if the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> ſhould ſucceed in their perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:46338:48"/>Enterpriſes, the Moſques of the great <hi>Allas</hi> moſt intimate Friend would be profan'd by his moſt invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Enemies, and that the important Place of <hi>Buda,</hi> where the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors had formerly made their Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, would no longer be inhabited but by Infidels. He added farther, That well knowing, he writ to a Man, who to a great Valor joyn'd no leſs Wit and Penetration, he forbare to mention many other Reaſons, which ſhould oblige him rather to Die, than Surrender the Place: ſince it was to be fear'd, the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> being inconſolable for ſuch a Loſs, would Sacrifice to his juſt Reſentment him, that ſhould prefer an infamous Life to the Glory he might acquire by finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Days in the Bed of Honor. Theſe two Letters, which were pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually deliver'd, had all the Effect, the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> could deſire. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who was in cruel Inquietudes for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no News of <hi>Zouglan,</hi> and equally fear'd the good or bad Succeſs of the Siege, perſwaded, that her Father would deliver her to <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> as ſoon as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were retir'd,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:46338:49"/>or the Place ſhould have capitulated, receiv'd with all the Joy imaginable her Lover's Letter. She bid the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negado, who brought it her, give her notice, when he ſhould return to the <hi>Muſulmens</hi> Camp, and comforted her ſelf for all the Diſcontents, the Abſence of <hi>Zouglan</hi> had caus'd her, by the Pleaſure, ſhe had, in reading over his Letter a thouſand times.</p>
            <p>Tho <hi>Cara Mahomet</hi> was reſolv'd to defend his Place to the utmoſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s Letter made ſo much Impreſſion on his Mind, that Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſending him the next day an Officer to Summon him to yield, and to inform him of the <hi>Turks</hi> Defeat, and the taking of <hi>Wierovitza</hi> by Count <hi>Leſly,</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd fiercely, That he pretended to revenge upon the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that were before <hi>Buda,</hi> the Loſſes, thoſe of his Party had receiv'd at <hi>Vicegrade, Peſt,</hi> and other Places, of which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had lately ſeiz'd. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd at the ſame time, That he would not accept any Quarter for himſelf, or his Garriſon, being reſolv'd not to give any to the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:46338:49"/>ſhould fall into his hands: and to the end he might perſwade him by Effects of the Truth, of what he ſaid, he caus'd Forty <hi>German</hi> Priſoners to be brought upon the Ramparts, and their Heads to be cut off in preſence of the Officer, telling him, he wiſht it were in his power to do as much to all the <hi>Chriſtian Army.</hi> The ſame day, after the Officer was gone back, the Beſieged made a vigorous Sally, and would have cleans'd the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and fill'd up the Works, had not Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> run thither himſelf, accompany'd with ſeveral Voluntiers, and oblig'd them to retreat, after a very obſtinate Fight, and very Bloody for both Parties. The Count <hi>d' Harrach,</hi> the Count <hi>de Naſſaw,</hi> the Count <hi>de Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemberg,</hi> and many other Voluntiers were Kill'd upon this occaſion. The <hi>Turks</hi> loſt there above Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men: which hindred them not from continuing to make ſuch frequent Sallies, that the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> were oblig'd to have always a double Guard in the Trenches, to repel them. They had advice about
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:46338:50"/>this time, that <hi>Cara Mahomet Baſſa</hi> was Kill'd by a Canon Shot; but <hi>Selim Aga,</hi> Father to <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who ſucceed him, teſtify'd no leſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of holding out, than his Predeceſſor had done. He aſſur'd the Garriſon, That the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> was taking care to relieve them; and to ſhew that he did not fear the <hi>Germans,</hi> nor would keep any Meaſure with them, he cut off the Heads of all the Priſoners, which had the unhappineſs to fall into his Hands.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> receiv'd Letters from the Grand <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier,</hi> who fent him word, he could not poſſibly give him the Succor he demanded, becauſe he had been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to ſend all the good Troops he had left to the <hi>Dardanelles,</hi> to <hi>Tenedos,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Chio,</hi> to hinder the Deſcent of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Forces, which had already taken St. <hi>Maure.</hi> He conjur'd him in ſuit to ſupply all things by his Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and Induſtry, and to hazard all, rather than let <hi>Buda</hi> be loſt. The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> aſſembled his Troops
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:46338:50"/>about <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> and prepar'd to put Relief into the Place, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army, which was very much weakned by the length of the Siege, and the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Sallies of the Beſieged, would not be in condition to hinder him; but the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Camp rais'd the Courage and Hopes of the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</hi> This Prince, having Landed his Forces, caus'd them to march in Battalia on a Line, which made a great Front that they might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more numerous to the Beſieged. He viſited afterwards all the Works, and choſe the Place, that appear'd to him moſt proper for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an Attack, which he began the ſame day by his Troops. They carried it on ſo far by the Care and Example of this young Prince, that they were oblig'd to ſtay, till that of the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> was ſufficiently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd, to the end they might make Lines of Communication between the two Attacks. But during all this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval, their Courage remain'd not unexercis'd: for the <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>k's,</hi> wondring
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:46338:51"/>to ſee an Attack ſo forward, made ſuch vigorous Sallies upon them, that they would infallibly have been dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from their Poſt, had not the Prince ſupported them by his firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and his Orders for the advancing of other Troops, which were in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condition to fight. <hi>Selim,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s Arrival, and the Vigor his Forces ſhew'd in their Attack, had diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted the Garriſon, and that the <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> began to draw together, and ſpeak of Surrendring the Place, had the Addreſs to perſwade them, That he had new Aſſurances, they ſhould be reliev'd within three Days; and to the end he might take out of their Minds thoſe flattering Hopes of Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation, which the Souldiers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd themſelves after a long Siege, he bethought himſelf of telling them, he knew from good hands, That the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in prejudice of the Articles they had granted the Garriſon of <hi>Wierovitza,</hi> had pillag'd all their Baggage, and afterwards put them all to the Sword; that the ſame Lot attended them, ſince they had to do
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:46338:51"/>with the ſame Enemies; and that it was for them to chooſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would live by giving the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> time to relieve them, or periſh by delivering themſelves to the Perfidious <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> This Artifice, tho it had no other Ground, but the Falſhood of five or ſix <hi>Croats,</hi> who pillag'd and ill entreated ſome <hi>Turks,</hi> that were ſtray'd in a Wood, fail'd not to prove advantageous to <hi>Selim.</hi> All the Garriſon engag'd by new Oaths to defend themſelves to the utmoſt Extremity, and conſented, That the firſt, who ſhould ſpeak of Capitulating, ſhould be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately Strangled.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice that the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> was drawing together an Army of Fifty thouſand Men for the Relief of <hi>Buda,</hi> caus'd Retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be made along the Lines, to the end he might hinder them
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:46338:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:46338:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:46338:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:46338:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:46338:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:46338:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:46338:55"/>from being aſſaulted by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and gave all the Orders neceſſary for their good Reception, if they preſented themſelves.</p>
            <p>Whil'ſt the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> was making an end to aſſemble his Troops, he underſtood, That <hi>Selim,</hi> who commanded in <hi>Buda,</hi> was ſlain; and that the Eldeſt <hi>Aga</hi> had taken the Command in his place. This News much diſcontented him, foreſeeing that his Miſtreſs would be afflicted at it, and fearing beſides, leſt the Loſs of a Man of his Merit might diminiſh the Ardor of the Beſieged. Scarce had he receiv'd this Advice, when the Renegado, who had already for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly brought him News from <hi>Buda,</hi> preſented himſelf before him, and after he had confirm'd the Death of <hi>Selim,</hi> gave him a Billet from <hi>Zaratima,</hi> which was written in theſe terms:</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:46338:55"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MY Father's Death has ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly afflicted me. I Fear alſo, leſt</hi> Cabſtan Baſſa <hi>pretend to take advantage of the Conſent, he had given him to Marry me. I find no Conſolation, but in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, your Love will furniſh you with Means to preſerve me from his Violence. In the mean time I counſel you to ſecure your ſelf of the famous</hi> Seraſquier<hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: for if he has all the good Qualities they tell us of here, he will not ſuffer</hi> Cabſtan <hi>to hinder me diſpoſing of an Heart my Love has deſtin'd you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> having read this Billet with all imaginable Joy, made her the following Anſwer:</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:46338:56"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>SElim<hi>'s Death much troubled me, becauſe of the Grief, I know, it has been to you. Quiet your Mind, and fear nothing from</hi> Cabſtan Baſſa. <hi>Aſſur'd of your Heart, all the Powers of the Earth cannot hinder my being happy. I am well enough with the</hi> Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier, <hi>to be able to anſwer you before hand, that he will with pleaſure employ all the Authority his Office gives him, and his Life it ſelf, if it be neceſſary, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all your Deſires. He is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to uſe extraordinary En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors, to force the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>Lines, relieve the Place, and raiſe the Siege. His Deſign cannot fail of Succeſs: for methinks, it will be impoſſible to reſiſt us, when we ſhall act to vanquiſh the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, that ſeparate me from you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:46338:56"/>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> gave the Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado Marks of Liberality, and promis'd him great Recompences; if he could deliver this laſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the ſame Felicity he had done the precedent. He order'd him alſo to aſſure the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Buda,</hi> he was upon his March, to approach the Place, and that he might reckon, he ſhould be ſuccor'd on the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, during all the Day. In Effect, his Impatience to ſee his Miſtreſs, and his Fear, leſt this new Governor might not defend himſelf with the ſame Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his Predeceſſors had done, oblig'd him to make his Army march the ſame day. He had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſent many Parties to tire the Beſiegers, and to endeavor the cutting off their Foragers. In fine, on the Twenty ſecond of <hi>September</hi> he drew near the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> Camp about Break of day,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:46338:57"/>and perceiving it was fortify'd with good Retrenchments, and that all the Army appear'd in a Diſpoſition to fight well, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach'd ſeveral Squadrons, which advanc'd as far as the Circumval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation on the ſide of Count <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian de Staremberg.</hi> The <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts,</hi> who were in <hi>Battalia</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd them with much vigor; but they had only Skirmiſhes, which laſted long enough, and the <hi>Turks,</hi> who were advanc'd too forward, loſt a great many more Men, than the <hi>Imperialiſts.</hi> In the mean time the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who had view'd the Camp, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he found new Difficulties in relieving the Place, or that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected his Foot, which were not yet come up, thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, and took no Benefit of three Sallies of above Fifteen hundred Men, which the Beſieged made on the ſide of the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:46338:57"/>at the time he approach'd the Camp. They had at firſt ſome Advantage, advancing as far as one of the Batteries, which they overthrew in a little time; but the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who loſt no opportunity to give Marks of his Courage, running thither at the Head of ſeveral Voluntiers, and three Squadrons of his Troops, repell'd them with ſo much Valor, that they were oblig'd to Retreat, abandoning two Pieces of Canon, they had began to bring thither. The <hi>Turks</hi> loſt above Three hundred Men on this occaſion. The <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> loſs would not have been ſo conſiderable, had not Count <hi>de Tilly,</hi> and other Perſons of Quality been then ſlain. On the Twenty third the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> attackt again the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Camp, at the Head of all his Horſe, but was beaten back with much vigor, loſing alſo
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:46338:58"/>two Standards. The Troops of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who had ſupported the <hi>Turks</hi> Efforts for many hours, were ſcarce entred into their Lines, when they were charg'd by the Garriſon, which made upon them a great Sally of Horſe and Foot; but the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> animated by the Example of their brave Prince, who gave them his Orders himſelf with a Reſolution above his Age, defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a long time, and the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts</hi> coming to their Aſſiſtance, the <hi>Turks</hi> were in fine beaten back. On the Twenty fifth the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> preſented himſelf again before the Lines, and diſpos'd his Troops in <hi>Battalia,</hi> making a ſhew, as if he would fight. Whilſt the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to reſiſt him, he detach'd Four thouſand Horſe, which he made march along an Hill, to gain a Paſſage, which was not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:46338:58"/>guarded, becauſe the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> judg'd it inacceſſible. They with much difficulty poſſeſt themſelves of it, and fell afterward upon a Quarter of the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> which was guarded only by two Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Horſe, and two Battal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Foot. They charg'd them, before they had time to look about them. During this Diſorder, the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who aim'd only to deceive the <hi>Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> Vigilancy, that he might get Relief into <hi>Buda,</hi> detach'd about Twelve hundred Foot, which, ſlipping along the Hill, got into the Place by favor of a Sally, the Beſieged made at the ſame time. In the mean time Major General <hi>Dunewald</hi> ran to aſſiſt the Regiments, that were envelop'd by the <hi>Turks.</hi> He hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred their being quite routed, and charg'd the Infidels ſo home, that he defeated them five Squadrons,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:46338:59"/>Killing above Three hundred Men. The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> ſatisfy'd with having reliev'd the Place, would no longer expoſe his Troops, but retreated in very good order. On the Morrow the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who expected the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> would not retire without Fighting, marcht forth to go attack him in his Camp; but the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> having advice of it, decamp'd about Midnight, and went to encamp ſo advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly between <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> and a great Marſh, that the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> judging it impoſſible to force him in ſo advantageous a Poſt, were oblig'd to return to their Camp. Tho the Beſieged wanted many Neceſſaries, and particularly Forage, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, the Succor they receiv'd, fail'd not to comfort them, and to give them great Hopes, they
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:46338:59"/>being perſwaded, That, ſince the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> had put Troops into the Place, he would find a Means to get in abundantly all things, of which they might have need. They alſo flatter'd themſelves, that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> would raiſe the Siege, without expecting the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> ſhould force them to it by giving them Battel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who had receiv'd her Lover's Billet, took a great ſhare in the publick Joy. Yet neither <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Letter, nor all, ſhe heard in commendation of the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who had the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation not to ſuffer any Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, could re-aſſure her. She thought her Lover flatter'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that his Paſſion gave him this great Confidence, ſhe remarkt in his Letters. <hi>Cabſtan</hi> perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally troubled her, and ſhe fear'd the laſt day of the Siege would be the Beginning of her Misfortunes,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:46338:60"/>prepoſſeſt, that this <hi>Baſſa</hi> would ſeize of all her Father's Eſtate, and of her ſelf too, without her being able to hinder it, ſince her Father dy'd in that Will. <hi>Zouglan</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to her a weak Protector againſt a <hi>Baſſa,</hi> ſo authoriz'd. Her Love and her Fear made her ſee a thouſand Dangers in the Aſſiſtance ſhe might expect from her Lover: for ſhe doubted not, but he had Reſolution enough to kill <hi>Cabſtan;</hi> but ſhe foreſaw, he would be immediatly puniſht for it, and that ſhe ſhould ſtill equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſe him. All theſe Reflexions cruelly perplext her, and ſhe ſaw ſome Moments, when ſhe knew not, whether ſhe ought to deſire the raiſing of the Siege. In fine, after having a long time tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her ſelf, ſhe found ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation in thinking, ſhe might avoid <hi>Cabſtan,</hi> by caſting her ſelf at the feet of the generous <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier,</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:46338:60"/>asking him his Protection, and informing him of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Reaſons ſhe had to prefer <hi>Zouglan</hi> before this <hi>Baſſa.</hi> Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated with this Hope, ſhe fail'd not to wiſh, the Siege were ended, and was already meditating upon all ſhe ſhould ſay to the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier,</hi> that ſhe might encline him to her Intereſt, when one of her Slaves acquainted her, That her Houſe was guarded by Fifty <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaries,</hi> and that the <hi>Aga,</hi> who commanded them, deſir'd to ſpeak with her. Her Fear, or rather her Love alarm'd, made her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently judge, they were <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa</hi>'s Emiſſaries, who would ſecure themſelves of her Father's Succeſſion, and perhaps of her Perſon; but the <hi>Aga,</hi> preſenting himſelf before her, told her, He was of the number of thoſe, that entred into the Place the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and that he had Orders from
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:46338:61"/>the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa</hi> to continue near her Perſon with Fifty <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> and to obey, whatever ſhe would command him; and if through Misfortune the Place ſhould be aſſaulted by the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> which was not probable, not to abandon her, but rather to be all cut in pieces, than to let her fall into their hands. <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima</hi> was extremely ſurpriz'd at the <hi>Aga</hi>'s Diſcourſe, not being able to comprehend, through what Motive the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> ſhould ſo much concern himſelf for a Perſon, he had never ſeen. Having reaſon'd long within her ſelf, to divine the cauſe of it, ſhe imagin'd the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps heard ſomething to her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and that he was without doubt of the ſame Humor with the greateſt part of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who always begin to ſatisfie their Love, before they declare their
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:46338:61"/>Paſſion to the Perſon, that cauſes it. This Thought gave her a thouſand Horrors, and engag'd her to make Reflexions on the unhappy Condition of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Women, who are rather their Husband's Slaves, than Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. She was troubled at the Education her Father had taken ſo much Care to give her: ſince it ſerv'd only to make her more ſeverely feel the Infelicity of her State. She thought nevertheleſs, ſhe ſhould be the moſt happy Perſon of her Sex, if ſhe might paſs her Life with her Lover; and maugre all the Reaſonings, ſhe had made, ſhe found a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pleaſure in reading over again <hi>Zouglan</hi>'s Letter, judging alſo, that, if it were true, the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier</hi> had a Merit proportion'd to his Reputation, it was not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, he might be her Lover's particular Friend, and might
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:46338:62"/>ſeek to give him an eſſential Proof of it, by the Care he took of a Perſon, which was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to him.</p>
            <p>Whilſt <hi>Zaratima</hi> was buſied with ſuch like Thoughts, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who was vext that he could not fight the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> viſited the Attack of his Troops, and finding it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much advanc'd, made them mount to the Aſſault. The Breach, which was not ſufficient, oblig'd them to retreat, and expect, till a Mine, that was to be ſprung, had made a greater. Tho the <hi>Christians</hi> Army began to want Victuals and Ammunition, and was extremely diminiſht by the frequent Combats, they had with the <hi>Turks,</hi> by the ordinary Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues of ſo long a Siege, and by the continual Sallies, they were forc'd to oppoſe; yet were they not rebutted. The Duke of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:46338:62"/>alſo declar'd, That he would not raiſe the Siege till the laſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, ſending to his States for other Troops, for Munitions of War, and Mouth, and for Cloths, to keep the Souldiers from the Cold, which began to incommode them. A <hi>French</hi> Engenier, who had ſerv'd in the King's Armies, being at that time arriv'd in the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> Camp, gave them new Hopes, they being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that a Man, which had made War under a Monarch, who never undertook Siege without Succeſs, might facilitate their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Place. The Count <hi>Bielk,</hi> whom we have ſeen Ambaſſador from <hi>Swedeland</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and who was a Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier in the Imperial Army, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented this Engenier to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> This <hi>Prince,</hi> who neglected nothing, that might contribute to the taking
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:46338:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:46338:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:46338:64"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:46338:64"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:46338:65"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:46338:65"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:46338:66"/>of <hi>Buda,</hi> gave him Employ the ſame Day. He wrought to make a great Mine, of which the Effect would have been infallible, had it not been overflown by the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in of Water from the Town. The <hi>Turks,</hi> who from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Siege foreſaw, that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> might take from them the Water of the <hi>Danow,</hi> digg'd a prodigious number of Pits, which were afterwards very ſerviceable to them: for the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> perſwaded of his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniers Capacity, had already diſpos'd his Troops, to go up to the Aſſault, aſſoon as this great Mine ſhould be Sprung; but at the time, when they no longer doubted of Succeſs, word was brought them, that many of theſe Pits were broken into the Miners Work, and had quite drown'd it. This hindred not the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> whom all theſe Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:46338:66"/>could not rebut, to give immediately new Orders for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning a Mine on another ſide.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier,</hi> having receiv'd a Reinforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Troops, and ſeeing, that the Beſiegers Army daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd, appear'd before the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> Camp at the Head of a great Body of Horſe. The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged made at the ſame time a vigorous Sally. Whilſt a Part of the Imperial Army was buſied in repelling it, and the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> amus'd the Horſe by Skirmiſhes, eight great Boats, laden with Men and Proviſions, ſent by the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Agria,</hi> paſs'd the <hi>Danow</hi> above <hi>Peſt.</hi> A Detachment of theſe <hi>Turks,</hi> having charg'd a a ſmall number of <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> who guarded the Redoubts, drove them away without much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, becauſe all the Troops were employ'd another way;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:46338:67"/>which was the Cauſe, this Relief got eaſily into the Place. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs this hindred not the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts,</hi> who expected great Effects from their Mines, to diſpoſe all things for the giving a general Aſſault; but a Deſerter of the Imperial Troops, being at that time got into <hi>Buda,</hi> diſcover'd to the Beſieged the Place where the Mines were, telling them alſo, That, if they had their Effect, it was impoſſible to avoid the Places being taken. This Advice gave no little Diſquiet to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and oblig'd them to work with an extreme Diligence, to diſcover the Mines by opening the Earth in many different pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to meet with the Beſiegers Works. Tho they had labor'd a whole day to no purpoſe, yet did not this ill Succeſs diſcourage them, They reſolv'd on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to hazard all, that they
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:46338:67"/>might hinder the Effect of theſe Mines, and having made a Sally with all the Troops they had left in a Condition to fight, they drove the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> as far as the Batteries, after having Kill'd them above Two hundred Men. A great Number of Laborers, who were come out of the Place, got in the mean time to the Mouth of the Mines, and drew out the Powder. All the Imperial Army took Arms, to repel this great Sally. The Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> ran thither in Perſon, and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated all things by his Example. Many Squadrons were made to March. The <hi>Turks,</hi> who would give their Laborers time to draw out the Powder, made many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges, before they retreated. They loſt a great many Men upon this occaſion; but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entred not into the Place, till after the Mines were empty'd,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:46338:68"/>and the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> Works en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ruin'd.</p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Army was very much weakned, that the Souldiers were diſcourag'd by ſo long a Siege, that the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd to tire them out by ſuch fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Alarms, and that the Cold and continual Rains would quite deſtroy the Troops, call'd a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of War, to deliberate upon the Reſolutions, they ought to take in ſo contrary Conjunctures. Some of the General Officers were for a continuation of the Siege, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting yet a good Effect from a new Mine, the Troops of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> had made; but the moſt part were of Opinion, That they ought to retreat in the beſt order they poſſibly could, to ſave the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Army. The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who hearkned only to his Glory, made a great
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:46338:68"/>Difficulty of conſenting to it. General <hi>Serini,</hi> who commanded this Prince's Troops, ſeeing, that the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> were determin'd to retreat, repreſented to him, that he was not reſponſible for the the Succeſs of the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> ſince it was not he that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took it, who only went to aſſiſt the Imperial Troops, mov'd by the Zeal, he had for Religion; That he ought to be very well contented with the Actions, he had done in the frequent Sallies, his Troops had born, and in the ſeveral Combats, in which they had beaten back the <hi>Seraſquier;</hi> That he might alſo aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the whole World would do him Juſtice, not having had leſs Ardor to take <hi>Buda,</hi> than he had ſhewn the year before to drive the Infidels from the Gates of <hi>Vienna;</hi> That, if the Succeſs had not been equal, his Glory was
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:46338:69"/>not therefore leſs, ſince it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That if the other Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> had imitated his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they might not only have taken <hi>Buda,</hi> and chas'd the <hi>Turks</hi> out of all the Places they held in <hi>Hungary,</hi> but have driven them alſo as far as <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and made the whole <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire tremble; That after all, great Princes are often expos'd to loſe Forces, but that the Glory they have acquir'd, is immortal, and continues always with them, and that they find Means to raiſe other Armies in their States; That in fine, an Aſſault was no longer to be thought of, ſince they could not give it without expoſing themſelves to be all loſt, nor avoid fighting between two Fires, the Garriſon, which had made good Retrenchments, being yet very ſtrong, and the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> always ready to charge the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:46338:69"/>as ſoon as they ſhould make any Motion to give a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſault.</p>
            <p>The young Prince, maugre the Heat of his Courage, let himſelf be perſwaded by ſuch good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Orders were given for Tranſporting, by the means of a Bridge of Boats, Eight thouſand Sick and Wounded, with the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and heavy Baggage into the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> All the Army, about Thirty thouſand ſtrong, Decampt afterwards, and having paſs'd the <hi>Danow,</hi> took their March by old <hi>Buda,</hi> for to go to <hi>Gran.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who held it for a Maxim, That one muſt make a Bridge of Gold for his Enemy, when they will retire, and who had an extreme Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to ſee his dear <hi>Zaratima,</hi> made not any Motion to charge the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> in their Retreat,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:46338:70"/>but entred into <hi>Buda,</hi> as ſoon as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had paſs'd the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>how.</hi> He was receiv'd with Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations and Shouts of Joy, which for a very long time hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him from being able to make himſelf heard. He gave a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Commendations to the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon and Inhabitants, and forgot nothing to perſwade the <hi>Aga,</hi> who commanded, that he might expect all manner of Recompence for the great Service he had done the whole <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. He found every where good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments, which made him judge, that the <hi>Germans</hi> had ruin'd their Army, if they had given a general Aſſault, as they would have done. He got rid with all the ſpeed, he poſſibly could, of the <hi>Aga,</hi> and other Officers, and feigning, he would honor the Memory of <hi>Selim,</hi> who had ſo well defended the Place,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:46338:70"/>caus'd himſelf to be conducted to his Daughter <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who was preparing to go forth of her Houſe, to caſt her ſelf at the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier</hi>'s Feet, and deſire his Protection againſt <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa;</hi> but as ſoon as ſhe faw <hi>Zouglan</hi> appear, the Preſence of this dear Lover re-aſſur'd her. She thought no longer of viſiting the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier;</hi> ſhe had even a great deal of Difficulty to conceal the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports of Joy ſhe felt, and to keep up in preſence of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, that environ'd this General, the Perſonage, ſhe repreſented, of a Daughter, afflicted for the Death of her Father. She was ſo buſied with her Love, and found ſo much Pleaſure in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Lover after ſo many Alarms, and ſo long an Abſence, that ſhe perceiv'd not the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, every one gave <hi>Zouglan,</hi> who having an Infinity of Orders
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:46338:71"/>to give, was oblig'd to quit his Miſtreſs, and to delay till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time the giving her account of his Elevation to the Office of <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> and of all other things, that had befallen him, ſince he ſaw her. <hi>Zaratima</hi> let him go out, perſwaded ſhe ſhould ſoon ſee him again. She began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh without conſtraint the Joy, this agreeable Interview had caus'd in her, when a Letter was brought her from <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> who writ to her, That not doubting, but ſhe was in the Reſolution to execute <hi>Selim</hi>'s laſt Will, he ſent her a Man, in whom he confided, who ſhould take care of all her Affairs, and ſhould Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct her to <hi>Temiſouar,</hi> where he promis'd to meet her, as ſoon as the Campaign was over. <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima,</hi> who always foreſaw, that <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa</hi> would give her ſome Trouble, would not ſee the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:46338:71"/>Man, he ſent her, determining to follow her firſt Thought, and ſecure her ſelf of the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s Protection, to deliver her ſelf by this General's Authority from the <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s Purſuits. In the mean time it being already late, and all being yet in Confuſion in the Town, ſhe delay'd her Viſit till the Morning, pleaſing her ſelf before-hand with imagining, ſhe ſhould by this Step ſhew her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſtrong Paſſion ſhe had for him. Tho ſhe reckon'd much on the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s Generoſity, ſhe ceas'd not to take care of her Adornment, perſwaded that fair Perſons have great Advantages to obtain what they deſire. There was already a great number of Officers and conſiderable Perſons with the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> when <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima</hi> arriv'd there, attended by many of her Slaves. The <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier,</hi> advertiz'd, that <hi>Selim</hi>'s
<pb facs="tcp:46338:72"/>Daughter deſir'd to ſpeak with him, found himſelf at firſt very much embarraſs'd. He went forth nevertheleſs to receive her, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd by a Crowd of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who gave him great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Zoug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> come to meet her, was no leſs perplext than he, foreſeeing, her Modeſty would have much to ſuffer, if ſhe muſt ſpeak to the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> in preſence of her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. She told him, ſhe had newly receiv'd a Letter from <hi>Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan Baſſa,</hi> which extremely trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled her, and that to ſhelter her ſelf from his Violence, ſhe was determin'd to deſire the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the generous <hi>Seraſquier. Zouglan</hi> anſwer'd her, ſmiling, that ſhe might be aſſur'd, the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier</hi> would give her a favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Audience. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that the Guards were at their Arms, and that every one
<pb facs="tcp:46338:72"/>was in a profound reſpect, lookt about for the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> and ſaw only her Lover, who acted as Maſter, and deſir'd her to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another Chamber, where he told her, ſhe might ſee the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier. Zaratima</hi> being entred, every one retir'd, except one of her Slaves, who continu'd with her. Then <hi>Zouglan,</hi> penetrated with Love and Joy, askt Pardon of his Miſtreſs, that he had no ſooner inform'd her of his Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, telling her, That himſelf was the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> and that he was oblig'd to her alone for this great Fortune, ſince he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways believ'd himſelf unworthy of her, whil'ſt he ſhould have only ordinary Employs, which are daily given to other <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s, and that the Violence of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had made him attempt all, that he might come to be <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier,</hi> and merit by it her Eſteem
<pb facs="tcp:46338:73"/>and Love. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> aſtoniſht, and raviſht at ſuch furprizing News, wept for joy, aſſuring him nevertheleſs, that, Tho he ſhould be Maſter of all the Crowns in the Univerſe, it could add nothing to the Tenderneſs ſhe had for <hi>Zouglan.</hi> The <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier,</hi> toucht with ſo obliging an Anſwer, promis'd her, Time ſhould never change the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuous Sentiments he had for her, and that he would regard her all his life, as his Divinity, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratreſs. They ſaid a thouſand tender and paſſionate things to each other. Afterwards the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier</hi> propos'd to her the going out of <hi>Buda,</hi> where ſhe ſaw only funeſt Objects, and offer'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company her to <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> where they might celebrate the Ceremony of their Marriage with all ſort of Magnificence. <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima</hi> conſented to it with Joy, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:46338:73"/>retir'd to diſpoſe her ſelf for her Departure the day following.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> having given the neceſſary Orders for re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the Fortifications of <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> accompany'd <hi>Zaratima</hi> to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba Regalis,</hi> declaring publickly, That he prepar'd to Marry her. <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa,</hi> who lov'd <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima,</hi> only in conſideration of her Father's great Wealth, thought no more of her, as ſoon as he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood he had ſo redoubtable a Rival; but the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who had always before his Eyes the great Obligations he had to the Grand <hi>Viſier Ibrahim,</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that this <hi>Viſier,</hi> lov'd <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima,</hi> and that he had heretofore written to him to <hi>Burſa,</hi> to make him the Confident of his Paſſion, and deſire him to ſeize this fair Perſon, made a ſcruple of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying her, believing he could not do it without betraying
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:46338:74"/>his Friend, and rendring himſelf unworthy his Amity. This cruel Reflexion caſt him into Irreſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which gave him great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes. His Love preſs'd him to ſatisfie himſelf, and to hearken to nothing, ſince it was in his own power to be happy, and to give Marks of his Tenderneſs and Acknowledgment to the fair <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who had ſav'd his Life, and lov'd him with ſo much Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but when he repreſented to himſelf, that the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> might think, his Letter had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him occaſion to ſee <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima,</hi> to become amorous of her, and conſequently to Marry her, without remembring his Friend's Intereſt, and that he might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps one day reproach him with his Perfidiouſneſs, the ſole thought of this imaginary Reproach ſtruck an horror in him; and maugre the violence of his Paſſion, he
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:46338:74"/>determin'd, before he Marry'd <hi>Zaratima,</hi> to write to the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> to acquaint him with the Obligations he had to <hi>Selim</hi>'s Daughter, and to give him an exact account of his Love, and of all the Progreſs he had made in his Miſtreſſes Mind, aſſuring him, That he lov'd her above his Life; and that he believ'd, he could not give a more eſſential Proof of the Attachment, he had for him, than the having delay'd his Marriage, till he was aſſur'd, he might do it without fear of expoſing himſelf to ſoſe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of ſo perfect a Friend. He ſent a Courier to the Port with this Letter, promiſing to reward him liberally, if he return'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a very ſhort time he ſet him. Tho <hi>Zaratima</hi> was very well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd with the Cares of her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and with the Honors every one paid her, ſince he had declar'd
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:46338:75"/>his Deſign to Marry her; ſhe could not comprehend why he delay'd the Ceremony, and what Reaſon he had to ſpeak no more to her of it. Her Modeſty made her ſupport her Diſcontent, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring five or ſix Days, without ſhewing any thing of it; but ſeeing, that the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> ſtill teſtify'd to her abundance of Love and Reſpect, and that neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he ſpake no more of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, ſhe entred into ſo great a Deſpair, that it was impoſſible for her to conceal it. The <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier,</hi> who in the Tranſports of his Love often repented the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity he had impos'd upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to expect his Friend's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer before he eſpous'd <hi>Zaratima,</hi> avoided entring into any diſcourſe with her about it, not daring to tell her the Reaſons, which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd him to delay his Marriage. There was ſtopt at this time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:46338:75"/>the <hi>Danow</hi> an <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Lady, who was a very handſom Perſon, and of very great Quality, as ſhe was going to ſee her Husband at <hi>Peſt,</hi> where he lay Sick. She was conducted to <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi> The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who has much Reſpect for Ladies, viſited her, and gave her all the Marks of Conſideration, ſhe could deſire in the State, in which ſhe was. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> who perpetually tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented her ſelf to penetrate the Reaſons of her Lovers pretended Indifference, believ'd, that he lov'd her not, and imagin'd, he had perhaps ſome particular Attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the <hi>German</hi> Lady, who had the Reputation to be a very fine Woman. <hi>Zaratima</hi> was in theſe Perplexities, when the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſquier,</hi> who found no true Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but in ſeeing his dear Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, came to her, and told her, That he had been ſo toucht with
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:46338:76"/>the <hi>ſtrong Paſſion,</hi> the Captive Lady teſtify'd for her Husband, that he had not been able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve any longer to deprive her of the Pleaſure to ſee him, but had caus'd her to be conducted to <hi>Peſt,</hi> without expecting her Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, which he was oblig'd to Pay for her to the Souldiers, that had ſtay'd her. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this Diſcourſe, that her Suſpicions were unjuſt, had a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Shame of the diſadvatageous Judgments, ſhe had made of her Lover, and not being able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port any longer the thought of his Infidelity, acknowledg'd to him with bluſhing, That the ſmall Earneſtneſs, he had ſhewn ſince their Arrival at <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> to finiſh their Marriage, had a little troubled her. The <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier,</hi> who never made uſe of any Artifice to diſguiſe his veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Sentiments, entirely impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:46338:76"/>to her the Letter he had written to the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> and the Reaſons, he had to ſhew this Deference to ſo faithful a Friend. <hi>You love me but with a very faint Paſſion,</hi> reply'd <hi>Zaratima</hi> in cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>ſince you could reſolve to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from the Grand</hi> Viſier<hi>'s Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity an Happineſs, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends only on your ſelf.</hi> Tears and Sighs hindred her going on. She retir'd into her Chamber, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to hear what her Lover ſaid to appeaſe her. As ſoon as ſhe was alone, her Imagination, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious to torment her, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to her the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> as an Ambitious Spirit, who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic'd his Love to his Fortune, and who troubled not himſelf at diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing his Miſtreſs, for to have occaſion to make his Court to the Grand <hi>Viſier.</hi> She paſs'd all the Night in cruel Inquietudes, and tho there were Moments, in
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:46338:77"/>which her Lover appear'd to her leſs culpable, her Love could not reliſh any Reaſons, which might ſerve to juſtifie him, and ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd ſtill very much offended at her Lover's Proceeding. The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who was in no more Repoſe, than his Miſtreſs, had an Anſwer from the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> much ſooner, than he expected. This firſt Miniſter, who had juſt learnt with all imaginable Joy, that the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> had rais'd the Siege of <hi>Buda,</hi> ſent the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> word, he was much troubled, that he had for his Sake delay'd his Felicity, and that in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration he had of his Services, he not only conſented he ſhould Marry <hi>Zaratima,</hi> but offer'd alſo to ſend him the faireſt Perſons of his <hi>Seraglio,</hi> if he deſir'd it. The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> who was extremely impatient to make his Peace with his dear <hi>Zaratima,</hi> went to her,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:46338:77"/>as ſoon as he had receiv'd this Anſwer, and told her, wholly tranſported with Joy, That he was in fine at the height of his Wiſhes, ſince he ſaw no longer any thing that could hinder his Happineſs. He preſented her at the ſame time the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi>'s Letter, but ſhe refus'd to ſee it, telling him, She had ſeriouſly reflected, on what ſhe ought to her Father's Memory, and that ſhe ſaw, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all the Precepts of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> ſhe could not diſpenſe with her ſelf from executing his Laſt Will, and Marrying <hi>Cabſtan Baſſa.</hi> The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> ſurpriz'd at ſo little expected an Anſwer, flatter'd himſelf nevertheleſs, that his Miſtreſs acted only through a Motion of Choler, and that ſhe ſpake againſt her own Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. He conjur'd her to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him, and no more to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber any thing, but their Love.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:46338:78"/>
               <hi>I am but too much poſſeſs'd with it,</hi> reply'd <hi>Zaratima; ſince I am reſolv'd, before I take any Party, to make a Journey to</hi> Mecha, <hi>to the end I may conſult the Great</hi> Cheq, <hi>to know, whether I can with a ſafe Conſcience Marry you.</hi> The <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> frighted at a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo contrary to his Love, made uſe in vain of all his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to deturn her from this Voyage, and was oblig'd through reſpect to retire, without being able to obtain any thing. He was ready to dy for Grief, when he reflected, That he had loſt all the Merit of a long and tender Paſſion through a Nicety, ill enough grounded; and without examining any farther, whether he had reaſon to write to the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> he believ'd himſelf very culpable, becauſe he had the Unhappineſs to diſpleaſe his dear <hi>Zaratima,</hi> to whom he had
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:46338:78"/>ſo great Obligations. He reproacht himſelf a thouſand times with his Ingratitude, and not ſeeing any Torment more cruel for him, than to live, without being lov'd by his Miſtreſs, he return'd to her with a Deſign to Puniſh himſelf, and dye at her Feet, if ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in her firſt Reſolution. <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratima,</hi> obſerving the Diſcontent which appear'd in her Lover's Face, repented, ſhe had put him in deſpair. The <hi>Seraſquier</hi> told her, He pretended no more to oppoſe her Will, ſince he well ſaw, that he merited the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities, which oppreſt him: he aſſur'd her alſo, that his Return to her was only to put himſelf to death before her eyes, and to ſacrifice to her a Life, ſhe had heretofore preſerv'd. <hi>Zaratima,</hi> mollify'd by her Lover's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and by the Deſpair, which appear'd in all his Actions, had
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:46338:79"/>not the power to ſee him any longer in ſo ſorrowful a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but let him underſtand, ſhe was toucht with his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The amorous <hi>Seraſquier</hi> embrac'd her Knees with all the Tranſports of Joy imaginable, and conjur'd her with ſo much inſtance, no longer to delay his Happineſs, that <hi>Zaratima</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him in fine to diſpoſe all things for their Marriage, which was celebrated a ſhort time after with as much Magnificence, as if the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> had eſpous'd a Princeſs of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Blood.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46338:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
